! don't know about you, it's just too hot today, isn't it?
Hari ini panas sekali, ya?
And it’s going to get even worse. Temperatures up in the mid-30s Celsius...
Dan akan makin panas. Suhu mendekati 30 Celcius...
...that's the mid-90s Fahrenheit, tomorrow, maybe even hitting 100.
...atau 90 Fahrenheit, besok mungkin bahkan sampai 100.
So, please, remember to cover up and stay cool...
Tetaplah tenang...
...with the hottest hits on your FM dial.
...dengan lagu-lagu terasyik di saluran FM-mu.
Come on, guys, time to go home.
Ayo, Anak-anak, waktunya pulang.
Come on, love, off you get.
Ayo, Sayang, turunlah.
-Do we have to? -Yes, we do.
-Haruskah kita pulang? -Ya.
V'll make you your favorite dinner to compensate.
Akan kubuatkan makan malam Kegemaranmu sebagai gantinya.
He squealed like a pig, didn’t he?
Dia menguik macam babi.
Yeah, brilliant punch, Big D. Did you see his face?
Tinjumu hebat, Big D. Kaulihat mukanya?
Hey, Big D.
Hai, Big D.
Beat up another 10-year-old?
Kau hajar anak 10 tahun lagi?
-This one deserved it. -Yeah.
-Dia pantas dihajar. -Ya.
-Five against one, very brave. -Well, you're one to talk.
-Lima lawan satu, nyalimu hebat. -Kau yang tak bernyali.
Moaning in your sleep every night? At least I'm not afraid of my pillow.
Ngigau waktu tidur tiap malam. Setidaknya aku tak takut bantal.
"Don't kill Cedric.”
“Jangan bunuh Cedric!"
Who's Cedric, your boyfriend?
Siapa Cedric, pacarmu?
-Shut up. -"He’s going to kill me, Mum.”
-Diam! -“Dia mau membunuhku, Bu!"
Where is your mum?
Di mana ibumu?
Where is your mum, Potter?
Di mana ibumu, Potter?
She dead?
Sudah mati?
Is she dead?
Sudah matikah dia?
Is she a dead Pott--?
Sudah mati, Pott--?
-Dudley. -Dudley, let’s go.
-Dudley. -Dudley, ayo.
-What’'s going on? -What are you doing?
-Ada apa ini? -Apa yang kaulakukan?
-I'm not doing anything. -We're getting out of here, Dudley.
-Tak kulakukan apapun. -Kita pergi dari sini, Dudley.
Come on, Dudley, hurry up.
Ayo, Dudley, cepat.
Dudley, run.
Dudley, lari.
Expecto Patronum.
Expecto Patronum.
Mrs. Figg.
Ny. Figg.
Don't put away your wand, Harry.
Jangan simpan tongkatmu, Harry.
They might come back.
Mereka mungkin datang lagi.
Dementors in Little Whinging, whatever next?
Dementor di Little Whinging, apa lagi berikutnya?
-Whole world’s gone topsy-turvy. -l don’t understand. How do you know--?
-Dunia sudah kacau balau. -Bagaimana anda tahu--
Dumbledore asked me to keep an eye on you.
Aku diminta Dumbledore mengawasimu.
Dumbledore asked you? You know Dumbledore?
Anda kenal Dumbledore?
After You-Know-Who killed that poor Diggory boy last year...
Setelah Kau-Tahu-Siapa bunuh bocah Diggory itu tahun yang lalu...
...did you expect him to let you go wandering on your own?
...kaupikir Dumbledore membiarkanmu berkeliaran sendirian?
Good Lord, boy. They told me you were intelligent.
Ya ampun. Katanya kau ini anak yang cerdas!
Now, get inside and stay there.
Ayo masuk ke rumah!
Expect someone will be in touch soon. Whatever happens, don't leave the house.
Ada teman yang akan menghubungimu. Jangan tinggalkan rumah.
it is hot. That's right, hot everywhere.
Udara panas sekali.
There's sweat. There's stifling.
Semua berkeringat.
Diddykins?
Diddykins?
Is that you?
Kaukah itu?
Duddy. Vernon, come quick.
Duddy. Vernon, cepat kemari!
We're going to have to take him to a hospital.
Dia harus ke rumah sakit.
Who did this to you, boy?
Perbuatan siapa ini, Nak?
Happy, are we, now?
Kau senang, ya?
You've finally done it. You've finally driven him loopy.
Akhirnya kaulakukan. Kaubuat dia jadi gila.
Vernon, don’t say that.
Vernon, jangan bilang begitu!
Well, just look at him, Petunia. Our boy has gone yumpy.
Lihatlah dia, Petunia. Anak kita jadi sinting.
I've reached my limit, do you hear?
Habis kesabaranku, kau dengar?
This is the last I'm gonna take of you and your nonsense.
Ini yang terakhir dari semua omong-kosongmu!
-Dear Mr. Potter. -What?
-Tn. Potter yang terhormat. -Apa?
The Ministry has received intelligence that at 6:23 this evening...
Kementerian menerima laporan bahwa jam 6.23 petang tadi...
...you performed the Patronus Charm in the presence of a Muggle.
...Anda mengucapkan Mantera Patronus di depan seorang Muggle.
As a clear violation...
Karena jelas melanggar Dekrit...
...of the Decree for the Reasonable Restriction of Underage Sorcery...
...Pembatasan Masuk Akal Bagi Penyihir Di Bawah Umur...
..-you are hereby expelled...
...dengan ini Anda dikeluarkan...
...from Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry.
...dari Sekolah Sihir Hogwarts.
Hoping you are well, Mafalda Hopkirk.
Semuga Anda baik-baik saja. Mafalda Hopkirk.
Justice.
Itulah keadilan.
He’s not very well.
Dia sedang sakit.
Sorry, Hedwig.
Maaf, Hedwig.
Very clean, these Muggles.
Sangat bersih, para Muggle ini.
-Tonks, for God's sake. -Unnatural.
-Tonks, ya ampun. -Tak wajar.
Professor Moody.
Profesor Moody.
-What are you doing here? -Rescuing you, of course.
-Mau apa di sini? -Menyelamatkanmu, tentu.
But where are we going? The letter said I've been expelled.
Kita mau ke mana? Aku sudah dikeluarkan dari Hogwarts.
You haven't been. Not yet. Kingsley, you take point.
Belum. Kingsley, kau terbang di depan.
But the letter said--
Surat itu--
Dumbledore persuaded the minister to suspend your expulsion...
Dumbledore meminta Menteri menunda pengeluaran dirimu...
-...pending a formal hearing. -A hearing?
-...sampai pemeriksaan resmi. -Pemeriksaan?
Don't worry. We'll explain everything when we get back to headquarters.
Jangan cemas. Akan kami jelaskan semua di Markas.
Not here, Nymphadora.
Jangan di sini, Nymphadora!
Don't call me Nymphadora.
Jangan sebut aku Nymphadora.
Stay in formation, everyone. Don’t break ranks if one of us is killed.
Tetap dalam formasi. Jika ada yang tewas, jangan keluar dari formasi.
Come on.
Ayo.
In you go, son.
Masuk ke rumah, Nak.
He almost killed Harry. If that isn’t proof enough....
Dia nyaris bunuh Harry, itu buktinya.
Yes, but guarding you-know-what is the most important....
Tetapi menjaga kau-tahu-apa itu yang terpenting.
We must trust Dumbledore on this.
Percayai Dumbledore soal ini.
Was he able to protect Harry last year? Well, tonight I say it’s time to take action.
Dia lindungi Harry tahun yang lalu? Malam ini kita harus beraksi.
Cornelius Fudge is a politician first and a wizard second.
Cornelius Fudge itu pertama-tama politisi, baru penyihir.
-His instinct would be to ignore it-- -Keep your voices down.
-Nalurinya untuk mengabaikan-- -Pelankan suaramu.
He’s getting stronger and stronger by the minute. We have to act now.
Dia makin kuat tiap saat. Kita harus bertindak sekarang.
-Harry. -Mrs. Weasley.
-Harry. -Ny. Weasley.
Heavens, you're all right.
Syukurlah, kau baik-baik.
Bit peaky, but I’m afraid dinner will wait until after the meeting's finished.
Agak lemah. Makan malam harus tunggu sampai rapat selesai.
Nope. No time to explain. Straight upstairs, first door on the left.
Tak ada waktu untuk menjelaskan. Langsung ke atas, pintu pertama.
Yeah.
Ya.
Mudblood, werewolves, traitors, thieves.
Darah lumpur, manusia serigala, penghianat, pencuri.
If my poor mistress knew the scum they let into her house...
Jika nyonyaku tahu sampah-sampah yang dibiarkan memasuki rumahnya...
...what would she say to old Kreacher?
...apa yang akan dia katakan?
Oh, the shame.
Memalukan sekali.
-Freaks. -There, there, mistress.
-Kumpulan aneh. -Sudahlah, Nyonya.
Scum of the earth. Not like it was in the days of my fathers.
Sampah dunia. Tak seperti pada zaman leluhurku.
Kreacher is here.
Kreacher di sini.
Oh, Harry.
Oh, Harry.
Are you all right? We overheard them talking about the Dementor attack.
Kau baik-baik? Kami dengar tentang serangan Dementor itu.
-You must tell us everything. -Let the man breathe, Hermione.
-Ceritakan semua. -Biarkan dia bernapas dulu.
And this hearing at the Ministry. It’s just outrageous.
Dan pemeriksaan di Kementerian itu. Keterlaluan!
I've looked it up. They simply can't expel you.
Sudah kupelajari, kau tak bisa dikeluarkan.
-It'’s completely unfair. -Yeah.
-Tak adil. -Ya.
There's a lot of that going round at the moment.
Banyak ketidak-adilan yang terjadi.
So, what is this place?
Tempat apa ini?
-It's headquarters. -Of the Order of the Phoenix.
-Ini Markas. -Orde Phoenix.
It's a secret society.
Kumpulan rahasia.
Dumbledore formed it back when they fought You-Know-Who.
Dibentuk Dumbledore saat melawan Kau-Tahu-Siapa.
Couldn't have put any of this in a letter, 1 suppose?
Mengapa tak kau surati aku soal ini?
I've gone all summer without a scrap of news.
Selama liburan musim panas aku tak tahu berita apapun.
We wanted to write, mate. Really, we did.
Kami ingin menyuratimu, Kawan. Sungguh.
-Only.... -Only what?
-Tetapi.... -Tetapi apa?
Only Dumbledore made us swear not to tell you anything.
Dumbledore melarang kami memberitahu kau apapun.
Dumbledore said that?
Dumbledore bilang begitu?
But why would he keep me in the dark? Maybe I could help.
Mengapa Dumbledore inginkan aku tak tahu apa-apa? Mungkin bisa kubantu.
I'm the one who saw Voldemort return...
Aku yang melihat Voldemort kembali...
...the one who fought him, who saw Cedric Diggory get killed.
...aku yang melawannya. Aku yang melihat Cedric Diggory dibunuh.
-Harry. -Thought we heard your dulcet tones.
-Harry. -Kami dengar suaramu.
-Don't bottle it up, though, mate. Let it out. -If you're all done shouting....
-Jangan pendam perasaanmu. Curahkan. -Jika selesai berteriak....
Do you wanna hear something a little more interesting?
Mau dengar sesuatu yang lebih menarik?
if anyone has a right to know, it's Harry. if it wasn't for Harry...
Yang paling berhak tahu, Harry. Jika bukan karena dia...
...we wouldn't even know Voldemort was back.
...kita tak tahu Voldemort kembali.
He's not a child, Molly.
Dia bukan anak kecil, Molly.
But he’s not an adult either.
Juga bukan orang dewasa.
-He's not James, Sirius. -Well, he's not your son.
-Dia bukan James, Sirius. -Dia bukan anakmu.
He's as good as.
Kuanggap anakku.
-Who else has he got? -Hey, Ginny.
-Punya siapa lagi dia? -Hei, Ginny.
-He's got me. -How touchingly paternal, Black.
-Dia punya aku. -Sungguh menyentuh, Black.
Perhaps Potter will grow up to be a felon, just like his godfather.
Mungkin Potter akan jadi penjahat seperti ayah-baptisnya.
Now, you stay out of this, Snivellus.
Jangan ikut campur, Snivellus.
-Snape's part of the Order? -Git.
-Snape anggota Orde? -Bodoh.
--about your supposed reformation.
#--tentang reformasi khayalanmu.
-1 know better. -So why don't you tell him?
-Aku tahu lebih baik. -Mengapa tak katakan padanya?
-Get off it. -Quick.
-Jangan sentuh itu. -Crookshanks!
-Get it up. -Crookshanks.
-Naikkan. -Crookshanks.
-Stop it. -Get off, you bloody cat.
-Hentikan. -Kucing keparat!
-Crookshanks. Leave it alone. -Get it up.
-Crookshanks. Biarkan itu. -Naikkan.
-Hermione, I hate your cat. -Bad Crookshanks.
-Hermione, aku benci kucingmu. -Crookshanks nakal.
Well, we'll be eating down in the kitchen.
Kita makan di dapur saja.
Just because you're allowed to use magic now...
Hanya karena kalian boleh menggunakan sihir...
...does not mean you have to whip your wands out for everything.
...tak berarti harus gunakan tongkatmu untuk segalanya!
Hi, Mum.
Hai, Bu.
You hungry, Harry?
Kau lapar, Harry?
You sure you're all right, Harry? Gave us quite a turn.
Kau baik-baik saja? Kami khawatir sekali.
Harry Potter.
Harry Potter.
Sirius.
Sirius.
This is very, very peculiar.
Aneh sekali.
It seems your hearing in the Ministry is to be before the entire Wizengamot.
Pemeriksaanmu akan dilakukan oleh seluruh Wizengamot.
I don’t understand. What has the Ministry of Magic got against me?
Aku tak mengerti. Mengapa Kementerian menghukum aku?
Show him. He'll find out soon enough.
Tunjukkan padanya. Nanti akan dia ketahui juga.
He’s been attacking Dumbledore as well.
Dia serang Dumbledore juga.
Fudge is using all his power, including his influence at the Daily Prophet...
Fudge menggunakan semua kuasanya, juga pengaruhnya di Daily Prophet...
...to smear anyone who claims the Dark Lord has returned.
...menjatuhkan yang bilang Pangeran Kegelapan kembali.
Why?
Mengapa?
He thinks Dumbledore’s after his job.
Menteri pikir Dumbledore mengincar jabatannya.
No one in their right mind could believe that--
Gila. Orang waras takkan berpikir Dumbledore mau--
Exactly the point. Fudge isn't in his right mind.
Itu soalnya. Fudge tidak waras.
It's been twisted and warped by fear.
Otaknya kacau karena takut.
Now, fear makes people do terrible things, Harry.
Takut membuat orang jadi kejam.
The last time Voldemort gained power...
Terakhir Voldemort meraih kekuasaan...
...he almost destroyed everything we hold most dear.
...hampir semua yang kita sayangi, dia hancurkan.
Now he’s returned, and I'm afraid the minister will do almost anything...
Kini dia kembali, aku takut Menteri akan lakukan apa saja...
...to avoid facing that terrifying truth.
...untuk menghindari kenyataan yang mengerikan itu.
We think Voldemort wants to build up his army again.
Kurasa Voldemort mau membangun kembali laskarnya.
Fourteen years ago, he had huge numbers at his command.
Empat belas tahun yang lalu laskarnya besar sekali.
And not just witches and wizards, but all manner of dark creatures.
Bukan hanya penyihir, juga segala macam makhluk kegelapan.
He’s been recruiting heavily, and we've been attempting to do the same.
Jumlah yang dia rekrut besar sekali, kami pun mencoba berbuat sama.
But gathering followers isn't the only thing he’s interested in.
Tetapi yang ingin dia capai bukan hanya menghimpun pengikut.
We believe...
Kami rasa...
... Voldemort may be after something.
...Voldemort mungkin menginginkan sesuatu.
Sirius.
Sirius.
Something he didn’t have last time.
Sesuatu yang tak dia dapatkan pada saat yang lalu.
You mean like a weapon?
Maksudmu, seperti senjata?
No. That's enough. He's just a boy.
Bukan. Cukup. Dia masih kecil.
You say more and you might as well induct him into the Order.
Jika kau bicara lagi, langsung saja masukkan dia ke Orde.
Good. I want to join. If Voldemort’s raising an army, then I want to fight.
Bagus! Aku gabung. Jika Voldemort punya laskar, aku mau bertarung.
Harry.
Harry.
You are hereby expelled.
Dengan ini kau dikeluarkan!
Before the entire Wizengamot.
Di hadapan seluruh Wizengamot.
Trains. Underground.
Kereta api. Di bawah tanah.
Ingenious, these Muggles.
Pintar sekali para Muggle ini.
Here we are.
Sudah sampai.
I’ve never used the visitors’ entrance before. Should be fun.
Aku belum pernah masuk lewat pintu tamu. Pasti menyenangkan.
Right. Good. I'll just get my Muggle money.
Baiklah. Kupakai saja uang Muggle-ku.
Terrible. Lost a lot of Galleons trading on the potions market.
Kemarin hari sial. Rugi banyak di pasar ramuan.
Daily Prophet, ladies and gentlemen. Anybody for Daily Prophet?
Siapa mau beli koran Daily Prophet?
Dumbledore: Is he daft, or is he dangerous?
DUMBLEDORE: GILA ATAU BERBAHAYA?
-Morning, Arthur. -Morning, Bob.
-Pagi, Arthur. -Pagi, Bob.
Interdepartmental memos.
Memo antar-departemen.
We used to use owls. Mess was unbelievable.
Dulu pakai burung hantu. Kotorannya di mana-mana.
Merlin’s beard. Thank you, Kingsley.
Demi jenggot Merlin! Terima kasih, Kingsley.
-They’ve changed the time of your hearing. -When is it?
-Pemeriksaan diubah waktunya. -Jadi kapan?
In five minutes.
Lima menit lagi.
Department of Mysteries.
Departemen Misteri.
And I’m confident, minister, that you will do the right thing.
Aku yakin, Menteri, akan kaulakukan hal yang benar.
Yes, but we must be--
Ya, tetapi kita harus--
Remember, during the hearing, speak only when you're spoken to.
Ingat, saat pemeriksaan, bicara hanya jika ditanya.
Keep calm. You've done nothing wrong.
Tetap tenang. Kau tak salah apapun.
As the Muggles say, truth will out.
Seperti pepatah Muggle, kebenaran akan terungkap.
Yes?
Ya?
I'm not allowed in, I’m afraid.
Sayang aku tak boleh masuk.
Good luck, Harry.
Semoga berhasil, Harry.
Disciplinary hearing of the 12th of August...
Pemeriksaan Disiplin, 12 Agustus...
..into offenses committed by Harry James Potter...
...perihal pelanggaran yang dilakukan Harry James Potter...
..resident at Number 4 Privet Drive, Little Whinging, Surrey.
...warga Jalan Privet No.4, Little Whinging, Surrey.
Interrogators: Cornelius Oswald Fudge, Minister of Mag--
Para pemeriksa: Cornelius Fudge, Menteri...
Witness for the defense.
Saksi tersangka!
Albus Percival Wulfric...
Albus Percival Wulfric...
...-Brian Dumbledore.
...Brian Dumbledore.
You got our message that the time and place of the hearing...
Terima pesan bahwa waktu dan tempat pemeriksaan...
-...had been changed, did you? - must have missed it.
-...diubah, 'kan? -Belum.
But by a happy mistake, l arrived at the Ministry three hours early.
Kebetulan aku tiba di Kementerian tiga jam lebih awal.
The charges?
Tuntutannya?
The charges against the accused are as follows:
Tuntutan terhadap tertuduh sebagai berikut:
"That he did knowingly...
“Walau dia tahu benar...
.and in full awareness of the illegality of his actions...
...tindakannya melanggar hukum...
...Pproduce a Patronus Charm...
...mengucapkan Mantera Patronus...
...in the presence of a Muggle.”
...di depan seorang Muggle."
-Do you deny producing said Patronus? -No, but--
-Kau bantah mengucapkan Patronus? -Tidak. Tetapi--
And you were aware that you were forbidden to use magic outside school...
Walau kau tahu itu terlarang di luar sekolah...
-...while under the age of 17? -Yes, I was, but--
-...bagi yang kurang dari 17 tahun. -Ya, tetapi saya--
Witches and wizards of the Wizengamot--
Para penyihir Wizengamot--
I was only doing it because of the Dementors.
Saya ucapkan hanya karena ada Dementor.
Dementors?
Dementor?
In Little Whinging?
Di Little Whinging?
That's quite clever.
Alasan cerdik.
Muggles can't see Dementors, can they, boy?
Muggle tak bisa melihat Dementor, 'kan, Nak?
-Highly convenient. -I'm not lying.
-Alasan pintar. -Saya tak berbohong.
-There were two of them, and if I hadn’t-- -Enough.
-Ada dua Dementor. Andai tak saya-- -Cukup!
I'm sorry to interrupt what I’m sure would have been a very well-rehearsed story...
Ceritamu itu pasti sudah kau hafal sekali...
...but since you can produce no witnesses of the event--
...tetapi karena kau tak punya saksi atas kejadian itu...
Pardon me, minister, but as it happens, we can.
Maaf, Menteri. Sebetulnya ada saksinya.
Please describe the attack.
Ceritakan serangan itu.
What did they look like?
Bagaimana rupa mereka?
Well, one of them was very large and the other rather skinny.
Satu badannya besar, satunya lagi agak kurus.
Not the boys. The Dementors.
Bukan anak-anak itu. Para Dementor itu.
Oh, right, right. Well, big.
Oh, ya, ya. Yah, besar.
Cloaked. Then everything went cold...
Berjubah. Lalu semua mulai terasa dingin...
..as though all the happiness had gone from the world.
...Seakan semua kebahagiaan lenyap dari dunia ini.
Now, look here. Dementors don’t just wander into a Muggle suburb...
Dengar. Dementor takkan begitu saja masuk ke pemukiman Muggle...
..-and happen across a wizard. The odds are astronomical.
...secara kebetulan bertemu penyihir. Boleh dikata mustahil.
I don't think anyone would believe...
Takkan ada yang percaya...
...the Dementors were there by coincidence, minister.
...Dementor di sana secara kebetulan, Menteri.
I'm sure I must have misunderstood you, professor.
Aku pasti salah memahami Anda, Profesor.
Dementors are, after all, under the control of the Ministry of Magic.
Dementor memang di bawah kendali Kementerian Sihir.
And it’s so silly of me, but it sounded for a moment as though...
Sungguh bodoh aku, tetapi sesaat terdengarnya seolah...
... you were suggesting that the Ministry had ordered the attack on this boy.
...kau isyaratkan Kementerian yang beri perintah menyerang anak itu.
That would be disturbing indeed, Madam Undersecretary...
Itu memang mengagetkan, Ibu Asisten Menteri...
...which is why I’m sure the Ministry will be mounting a full-scale inquiry...
...dan aku yakin Kementerian akan melakukan penyelidikan seksama...
...into why the two Dementors were so very far from Azkaban...
...mengapa kedua Dementor berada sangat jauh dari Azkaban...
...-and why they mounted an attack without authorization.
...dan mengapa mereka melakukan penyerangan tanpa izin.
Of course, there is someone...
Pasti ada seseorang...
...who might be behind the attack.
...di balik penyerangan itu.
Cornelius, l implore you to see reason.
Cornelius, kumohon gunakan akal-sehatmu.
The evidence that the Dark Lord has returned is incontrovertible.
Bukti bahwa Pangeran Kegelapan sudah kembali tak terbantahkan.
He is not back.
Dia tidak kembali!
In the matter of Harry Potter...
Soal Harry Potter...
...the law clearly states...
...hukum jelas menyatakan...
...that magic may be used before Muggles in life-threatening situations.
...Sihir bisa digunakan di depan Muggle dalam keadaan jiwa terancam.
Laws can be changed if necessary, Dumbledore.
Hukum bisa diubah jika perlu, Dumbledore.
Clearly. Has it become practice to hold a full criminal trial...
Jelas. Sudah jadi kebiasaankah mengadakan pengadilan kriminal...
...to deal with a simple matter of underage magic?
...untuk menghukum pelanggaran kecil anak di bawah umur?
Those in favor of conviction?
Yang setuju tertuduh dihukum?
Those in favor of clearing the accused of all charges?
Yang setuju membebaskan tertuduh dari semua tuntutan?
Cleared of all charges.
Dibebaskan dari semua tuntutan.
Professor.
Profesor.
Padfoot. Are you barking mad?
Padfoot! Kau sudah gila?
You'll blow the entire operation.
Nanti semuanya terbongkar.
Sirius, what are you doing here? If somebody sees you....
Sirius apa yang kaulakukan di sini? Jika ada yang melihatmu.
I had to see you off, didn’t I?
Aku harus melihatmu pergi.
What's life without a little risk?
Apa arti hidup ini jika tanpa risiko?
I don’t wanna see you get chucked back in Azkaban.
Aku tak mau kau dipenjara di Azkaban lagi.
Don't worry about me.
Jangan khawatir soal aku.
Anyway, I wanted you to have this.
Walau begitu, kuingin kau memiliki foto ini.
Original Order of the Phoenix.
Pendiri asli Orde Phoenix.
Marlene McKinnon.
Marlene McKinnon.
She was killed two weeks after this was taken.
Dia dibunuh dua minggu setelah foto ini dibuat.
Voldemort wiped out her entire family.
Seluruh keluarganya dihabisi Voldemort.
Frank and Alice Longbottom.
Frank dan Alice Longbottom.
Neville’s parents.
Orangtua Neville.
They suffered a fate worse than death, you ask me.
Nasibnya lebih buruk daripada mati.
It's been 14 years.
Itu empat belas tahun yang lalu.
And still a day doesn't go by I don't miss your dad.
Namun tak sehari pun lewat tanpa aku merindukan ayahmu.
Do you really think there’s going to be a war, Sirius?
Kau rasa akan ada perang, Sirius?
It feels like it did before.
Rasanya seperti yang terjadi dulu.
You keep it.
Simpan foto itu.
Anyway, I suppose you're the young ones now.
Kalian generasi muda kita sekarang.
I'll see you at the train.
Sampai bertemu di kereta api.
Bye-bye, darling.
Da da, Sayang.
l love you.
Aku sayang padamu.
Hold my hand, lovey.
Pegang tanganku, Sayang.
There they are. They're in the far carriage.
Itu mereka. Di gerbong yang paling jauh.
Bye.
Da.
I'm surprised the Ministry's still letting you walk around free.
Heran Kementerian masih membiarkan kau bebas, Potter.
Better enjoy it while you can.
Nikmati saja selagi bisa.
l expect there’s a cell in Azkaban with your name on it.
Tak lama lagi kau akan mendekam di Azkaban.
-What'd I tell you? Complete nutter. -Just stay away from me!
-Apa kataku! Dia gila. -Jauhi aku saja!
It’s only Malfoy.
Begitulah Malfoy.
What'd you expect?
Mau bagaimana lagi?
Hi, guys.
Hai, Kalian.
-Hey, Neville. -Hey there, Neville.
-Hei, Neville.
What is it?
Apa itu?
-What's what? -That. Pulling the carriage.
-Apa? -Itu. Yang menarik kereta itu.
Nothing’s pulling the carriage, Harry.
Tak ada yang menarik kereta, Harry.
It’s pulling itself, like always.
Jalan sendiri, seperti biasa.
You're not going mad.
Kau tidak jadi gila.
I can see them too.
Kulihat juga mereka.
You're just as sane as I am.
Kau sama warasnya dengan aku.
Everyone, this is Loony Love--
Kalian, ini Loony (sinting) Love--
Luna Lovegood.
Luna Lovegood.
What an interesting necklace.
Kalungmu menarik.
It's a charm, actually.
Sebenarnya ini jimat pelindung.
Keeps away the Nargles.
Menjauhkan Nargle.
Hungry.
Aku lapar.
I hope there's pudding.
Kuharap ada puding.
-What’s a Nargle? -No idea.
-Apa itu Nargle? -Tidak tahu.
Good evening, children.
Selamat petang, Anak-anak.
Now, we have two changes in staffing this year.
Tahun ini ada dua perubahan pengajar.
We're pleased to welcome back Professor Grubbly-Plank...
Kita ucapkan selamat kembali Profesor Grubbly Plank...
...who’'ll be taking Care of Magical Creatures...
...yang akan mengajar Pemeliharaan Satwa Gaib...
... while Professor Hagrid is on temporary leave.
...sementara Profesor Hagrid sedang cuti.
We also wish to welcome our new Defense Against the Dark Arts teacher...
Kita sambut juga guru baru Pertahanan terhadap Ilmu Hitam...
...Professor Dolores Umbridge.
...Profesor Dolores Umbridge.
And I'm sure you'll all join me in wishing the professor good luck.
Aku yakin kalian ikut bersamaku menyambut Profesor.
Now, as usual, our caretaker, Mr. Filch, has asked me to remind you--
Seperti biasa, pengurus gedung kita, Pak Filch, mengingatkan--
She was at my hearing. She works for Fudge.
Dia ada di pemeriksaanku. Dia orangnya Fudge.
Thank you, headmaster, for those kind words of welcome.
Terima kasih, Kepala Sekolah, atas sambutannya yang baik.
And how lovely to see all your bright...
Sungguh menyenangkan melihat wajah kalian semua...
.. happy faces smiling up at me.
...yang bahagia tersenyum padaku.
I'm sure we're all going to be very good friends.
Aku yakin kita semua akan jadi teman yang baik.
-That’s likely.
-Mungkin saja.
The Ministry of Magic has always considered...
Kementerian Sihir selalu menganggap...
...the education of young witches and wizards to be of vital importance.
...pendidikan para penyihir muda hal yang sangat penting.
Although each headmaster...
Walau setiap Kepala Sekolah memberikan...
...has brought something new to this historic school...
...Sesuatu yang baru pada sekolah bersejarah ini...
...progress for the sake of progress must be discouraged.
...perubahan demi perubahan harus dikurangi.
Let us preserve what must be preserved...
Kita harus melestarikan yang harus dilestarikan...
...perfect what can be perfected...
...menyempurnakan yang bisa disempurnakan...
..-and prune practices that ought to be prohibited.
...dan hapuslah kebiasaan yang harusnya dilarang.
Thank you, Professor Umbridge. That really was most illuminating.
Terima kasih, Profesor Umbridge. Itu sungguh mencerahkan.
-Illuminating? What a load of waffle. -What’s it mean?
-Mencerahkan? Itu omong kosong. -Apa maksud ucapannya?
Magic is forbidden in the corridors....
Sihir dilarang di sepanjang koridor....
It means the Ministry's interfering at Hogwarts.
Maksudnya Kementerian mau mengatur yang diajarkan di Hogwarts.
Dean, Seamus.
Dean, Seamus.
-Good holiday? -All right.
-Senang liburan? -Lumayan.
Better than Seamus’, anyway.
Lebih menyenangkan dari Seamus.
Me mum didn’t want me to come back this year.
Ibuku tak ingin aku ke Hogwarts lagi.
-Why not? -Let me see. Because of you.
-Mengapa? -Karena kau.
The Daily Prophet's been saying a lot of things about you and Dumbledore.
Daily Prophet banyak menulis tentang kau, Harry, dan Dumbledore.
What, your mum believes them?
Ibumu percaya?
Nobody was there the night Cedric died.
Saat Cedric mati hanya ada kau.
I guess you should read the Prophet, then, like your stupid mother.
Baca saja koran itu seperti ibumu yang bodoh.
-Don't talk about my mother. -l'll have a go at anyone that calls me a liar.
-Jangan hina ibuku. -Kuhina yang menyebutku pembohong.
-What’'s going on? -He’s mad, is what's going on.
-Ada apa? -Dia marah-marah.
Do you believe the rubbish he’s come out with about You-Know-Who?
Kau percaya omong-kosongnya tentang Kau-Tahu-Siapa?
Yeah. I do.
Aku percaya.
Has anyone else got a problem with Harry?
Siapa punya masalah dengan Harry?
-You all right? -Fine.
-Kau baik-baik? -Ya.
Seamus was bang out of order, mate.
Reaksi Seamus berlebihan.
-But he'll come through, you'll see. -l said, I'm fine, Ron.
-Tetapi akan berubah. -Kataku aku baik-baik, Ron!
Right. I'll just leave you to your thoughts, then.
Baik. Kalau begitu takkan kuganggu.
Harry.
Harry.
Bring it over here. Over here.
Bawa ke sini. Ke sini.
Oh, go on, Seamus. Go on, get it.
Ayo, Seamus. Ayo, hantam itu.
Good morning, children.
Selamat pagi, Anak-anak.
Ordinary Wizarding Level examinations.
Ujian Tingkat Sihir Umum.
O-W-Ls.
Disingkat O.W.L.
More commonly known as OWLs.
Lebih dikenal sebagai OWL.
Study hard and you will be rewarded.
Belajar yang rajin, kalian akan diganjar.
Fail to do so, and the consequences may be severe.
Tidak belajar, akan kalian rasakan akibatnya yang berat.
Your previous instruction in this subject has been disturbingly uneven.
Pelajaran kalian dalam subyek ini banyak terputus.
But you'll be pleased to know, from now on...
Tetapi kalian boleh senang, mulai sekarang...
...you will be following a carefully structured, Ministry-approved...
...akan kalian pelajari ilmu yang terencana, disetujui Kementerian...
...course of defensive magic. Yes?
...Pertahanan terhadap Sihir. Ya?
There’s nothing in here about using defensive spells?
Di sini tak ada soal penggunaan mantera pertahanan?
Using spells?
Penggunaan mantera?
Well, can’t imagine why you would need to use spells in my classroom.
Buat apa gunakan mantera di kelasku?
We're not gonna use magic?
Takkan gunakan sihir?
You'll be learning about defensive spells in a secure, risk-free way.
Akan kalian pelajari mantera pertahanan tanpa ada akibatnya.
What use is that? If we're attacked, it won't be risk-free.
Jika diserang, pasti akan ada akibatnya.
Students will raise their hands when they speak in my class.
Angkat tangan jika mau bicara!
It is the view of the Ministry...
Menurut pendapat Kementerian...
...that a theoretical knowledge will be sufficient...
...pengetahuan teori sudah cukup...
...to get you through your examinations...
...untuk lulus ujian.
.. Which, after all, is what school is all about.
Sekolah 'kan untuk lulus ujian dan diwisuda.
And how's theory supposed to prepare us for what's out there?
Bagaimana teori mempersiapkan kami terhadap yang ada di luar?
There is nothing out there, dear.
Tak ada apa-apa di luar.
Who do you imagine wants to attack children like yourself?
Siapa mau menyerang anak seperti kau?
Oh, I don’t know. Maybe Lord Voldemort.
Entah. Mungkin Lord Voldemort.
Now, let me make this quite plain.
Akan kukatakan sejelasnya agar kalian mengerti.
You have been told...
Ada yang memberitahu kalian...
...that a certain dark wizard is at large once again.
...ada seorang penyihir hitam yang kembali lagi.
-This is a lie. -It’s not a lie. saw him. I fought him.
-Itu suatu kebohongan. -Tidak! Dia kulihat! Kulawan!
Detention, Mr. Potter.
Kau dihukum, Tn Potter!
Cedric Diggory dropped dead of his own accord?
Jadi Cedric Diggory mati sendiri?
Cedric Diggory’s death was a tragic accident.
Kematian Cedric Diggory kecelakaan menyedihkan.
It was murder. Voldemort killed him.
Mati dibunuh Voldemort!
Enough!
Cukup!
Enough.
Cukup.
See me later, Mr. Potter. My office.
Temui aku nanti, Tn Potter. Di kantorku.
Come in.
Masuk.
Good evening, Mr. Potter.
Selamat petang, Tn Potter.
Sit.
Duduk.
You're going to be doing some lines for me today, Mr. Potter.
Tulis sebuah kalimat berkali-kali untukku, Tn Potter.
No, not with your quill.
Tidak dengan penamu.
Going to be using a rather special one of mine.
Tulis dengan pena istimewaku.
Now...
Sekarang...
...[ want you to write, “I must not tell lies.”
...tulis "Aku tidak boleh bohong."
How many times?
Berapa kali?
Well, let’s say for as long as it takes for the message to sink in.
Katakanlah, sampai tulisannya terlihat di tanganmu.
You haven't given me any ink.
Mana tintanya?
Oh, you won't need any ink.
Kau tak memerlukan tinta.
Yes?
Ya?
-Nothing. -That’s right.
-Tidak. -Jawaban yang tepat.
Because you know, deep down...
Karena di dalam hatimu...
..-you deserve to be punished.
...kau sadar kalau kau patut dihukum.
Don’t you, Mr. Potter?
Ya 'kan, Tn Potter?
Go on.
Teruskan.
-Skiving Snackboxes. -Sweets that make you ill.
-Kue Skiving. -Yang membuatnu sakit.
Get out of class whenever you like.
Alasan untuk bolos.
Obtain hours of pleasure from unprofitable boredom.
Dapatkan berjam-jam kesenangan dari kejenuhan.
Care for another?
Mau lagi?
-I'm not asking you to write all of it for me. -Please.
Aku tak minta kau tulis semua untukku.
I've been busy studying for these stupid OWL exams.
Aku cuma sedang belajar untuk ujian OWL.
Pll do the introduction. That's all.
Kutulis pembukaannya saja.
Hermione, you're honestly the most wonderful person I've ever met.
Hermione, kau sungguh orang terbaik yang kukenal.
-And if I’m ever rude to you again.... -l'll know you've gone back to normal.
-Jika aku kasar lagi.... -Berarti kau normal lagi.
What’s wrong with your hand?
Mengapa tanganmu?
Nothing.
Tidak apa-apa.
The other hand.
Tangan satunya.
-You've got to tell Dumbledore. -No.
-Beritahu Dumbledore. -Jangan.
Dumbledore’s got enough on his mind right now.
Sudah cukup beban pikirannya.
I don’t want to give Umbridge the satisfaction.
Umbridge takkan kuberi kepuasaan.
Bloody hell, Harry. The woman’s torturing you.
Aduh, Harry. Wanita itu menyiksamu!
-lIf the parents knew about this.... -l haven't got any of those, have I, Ron?
-Jika orangtuamu tahu.... -Mereka sudah tak ada, Ron.
Harry, you've got to report this.
Harry, ini harus kaulaporkan.
-It’s perfectly simple. You're being-- -No, it’s not.
-Begitu kaulaporkan, selesai-- -Tak semudah itu.
Hermione, whatever this is, it’s not simple.
Hermione, penyebabnya tak sederhana.
You don’t understand.
Kau tak mengerti.
Then help us to.
Bantu kami agar mengerti.
Dear Padfoot...
Yth. Padfoot...
...f hope you're all right.
...kuharap kau baik-baik saja.
it's starting to get colder here. Winter is definitely on the way.
Mulai dingin di sini. Musim dingin segera tiba.
In spite of being back at Hogwarts, ! feel more alone than ever.
Walau sudah di Hogwarts lagi, aku merasa lebih sendirian.
i know you, of all people, will understand.
Aku tahu kau pasti mengerti.
Hello, Harry Potter.
Halo, Harry Potter.
-Your feet. Aren't they cold? -Bit.
-Kakimu. Tak dingin? -Sedikit.
Unfortunately, all my shoes have mysteriously disappeared.
Sialnya semua sepatuku hilang secara misterius.
I suspect Nargles are behind it.
Aku curiga, Nargle pelakunya.
-What are they? -They’re called Thestrals.
-Apa mereka itu? -Disebut Thestral.
They're quite gentle, really, but people avoid them because they're a bit....
Sebenarnya sangat baik, tetapi dijauhi orang karena agak...
Different.
...berbeda.
But why can't the others see them?
Mengapa orang lain tak bisa melihat mereka?
They can only be seen by people who've seen death.
Hanya terlihat oleh orang yang pernah melihat kematian.
So you've known someone who's died, then?
Jadi kau pernah melihat orang mati?
My mum.
Ibuku.
She was quite an extraordinary witch, but she did like to experiment...
Dia penyihir luar biasa, tetapi suka bereksperimen...
..-and one day, one of her spells went badly wrong.
...SUatu hari Ibu tewas oleh manteranya sendiri.
-l was 9. -I'm sorry.
-Saat umurku 9 tahun. -Aku turut menyesal.
Yes, it was rather horrible.
Ya, agak mengerikan.
I do feel very sad about it sometimes, but I’ve got Dad.
Kadang aku sangat sedih, tetapi masih ada ayah.
We both believe you, by the way.
Kami percaya ucapanmu.
That He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named is back, and you fought him...
Bahwa Dia-Yang-Namanya-Tak-Boleh- Disebut sudah kembali dan kaulawan...
...and the Ministry and the Prophet are conspiring against you.
...dan Kementerian dan The Prophet menentang kau dan Dumbledore.
Thanks. It seems you're about the only ones that do.
Hanya kau yang percaya.
I don’t think that’s true.
Itu tak benar.
But I suppose that's how he wants you to feel.
Kurasa dia ingin kau merasa begitu.
What do you mean?
Maksudmu?
Well, if 1 were You-Know-Who...
Andai aku ini Kau-Tahu-Siapa...
...['d want you to feel cut off from everyone else...
...akan kubuat kau merasa dijauhi semua orang...
...because if it’s just you alone...
...karena jika hanya kau sendirian...
..-you’re not as much of a threat.
...kau tak begitu berbahaya.
-Do you ever stop eating? -What? I’m hungry.
-Pernahkah kau berhenti makan? -Apa? Aku lapar.
Harry.
Harry.
Can I join you?
Boleh ikut duduk?
Pardon me, professor, but what exactly are you insinuating?
Maaf Profesor, kau menuduhku apa?
lam merely requesting that when it comes to my students...
Aku hanya minta jika menghukum para siswaku...
..-you conform to the prescribed disciplinary practices.
...lakukan sesuai metode pendisiplinan yang disetujui.
So silly of me, but it sounds...
Maafkan aku, tapi kedengarannya...
..as if you're questioning my authority in my own classroom...
...Sepertinya kau ragukan wewenangku, di kelasku sendiri...
...Minerva.
...Minerva.
Not at all, Dolores, merely your medieval methods.
Sama-sekali tidak, Dolores. Hanya metode abad pertengahanmu.
lam sorry, dear.
Maaf saja.
But to question my practices is to question the Ministry...
Meragukan metodeku berarti meragukan Kementerian...
..and by extension, the minister himself.
...yang berarti meragukan Menteri.
lam a tolerant woman...
Aku wanita toleran...
...but the one thing I will not stand for is disloyalty.
...Satu hal yang tak kutolerir: ketidaksetiaan.
Disloyalty.
Ketidaksetiaan.
Things at Hogwarts are far worse than I feared.
Kondisi di Hogwarts lebih parah dari yang kukhawatirkan.
Cornelius will want to take immediate action.
Cornelius akan menginginkan tindakan segera.
What's happened to Dumbledore?
Bagaimana Dumbledore?
Having already revolutionized...
Setelah merombak...
...the teaching of Defense Against the Dark Arts...
...pengajaran Pertahanan Terhadap Sihir Hitam...
.--Dolores Umbridge will, as high inquisitor, have powers...
...Umbridge sebagai Inkuisitor Agung punya kekuasaan...
...to address the seriously falling standards at Hogwarts School.
...memperbaiki standar yang merosot di Sekolah Hogwarts.
Just one question, dear.
Satu pertanyaan, Sayang.
You've been in this post how long, exactly?
Sudah berapa lama tepatnya kau mengajar di sini?
You applied first for the Defense Against the Dark Arts post, is that correct?
Kau mulanya melamar jadi guru Pertahanan Terhadap Sihir Hitam?
Yes.
Ya.
But you were unsuccessful?
Tetapi tak berhasil?
Obviously.
Sudah pasti.
Could you please predict something for me?
Bisa ramalkan sesuatu untukku?
I'm sorry?
Maaf?
Move those mouths.
Gerakkan mulut kalian!
One teensy little prophecy?
Hanya ramalan tak penting?
Pity.
Sayang sekali.
No, wait. Wait, no. I think I do see something.
Tunggu! Kulihat sesuatu.
Yes, 1 do. Something dark.
Sesuatu yang gelap.
You are in grave danger.
Kau dalam bahaya besar.
Lovely.
Bagus sekali.
Cho. What's going on?
Cho. Ada apa?
It's Professor Trelawney.
Profesor Trelawney.
Sixteen years I've lived and taught here.
Sudah enam belas tahun aku tinggal dan mengajar di sini.
Hogwarts is my home.
Hogwarts adalah rumahku.
You can't do this.
Kau tak bisa melakukan ini.
Actually, I can.
Tepatnya aku bisa.
Something you'd like to say?
Kau mau mengatakan sesuatu?
Oh, there are several things I would like to say.
Aku mau mengatakan banyak hal.
There....
Sudah, sst.
Professor McGonagall, might I ask you to escort Sybil back inside?
Profesor McGonagall, bisa tolong antarkan masuk Sybil?
Sybil, dear. This way.
Sybil, Sayang. Ikut aku.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Dumbledore, may I remind you that under the terms...
Dumbledore, kuingatkan, sesuai...
...of Educational Decree Number 23, as enacted by the minister--
...Dekrit Pendidikan No.23 yang disahkan oleh Menteri--
You have the right to dismiss my teachers.
Kau berwenang memecat guru.
You do not, however, have the authority to banish them from the grounds.
Tetapi kau tak berwenang mengusirnya dari tempat ini.
That power remains with the headmaster.
Tetap wewenang Kepala Sekolah.
For now.
Sementara ini.
Don't you all have studying to do?
Kalian tak belajar?
Professor.
Profesor.
Professor?
Profesor?
Professor Dumbledore. Professor!
Profesor Dumbledore. Profesor!
Professor Dumbledore.
Profesor Dumbledore.
That foul, evil, old gargoyle.
Jahat, setan tua!
We're not learning how to defend ourselves. We're not learning how to pass our OWLs.
Kita tak belajar mempertahankan diri. Tak belajar bagaimana lulus Ujian OWL.
She's taking over the entire school.
Sekolah dia kuasai.
Security has been and will remain the Ministry's top priority.
Prioritas utama Kementerian tetap keamanan masyarakat penyihir.
Furthermore, we have convincing evidence...
Lagi pula ada bukti meyakinkan...
...that these disappearances are the work...
...lenyapnya warga adalah ulah...
...0f notorious mass murderer Sirius Black.
..pembunuh masal terkenal Sirius Black.
Harry.
Harry.
Sirius.
Sirius.
-What are you doing here? -Answering your letter.
-Mau apa di sini? -Menanggapi suratmu.
You said you were worried about Umbridge. What's she doing?
Kau cemas soal Umbridge.
Training you to kill half-breeds?
Kau dilatih membunuh darah-campuran?
-She’s not letting us use magic at all. -Well, I’m not surprised.
-Dia melarang kami memakai sihir. -Tidak heran.
The latest intelligence is that Fudge doesn’t want you trained in combat.
Menurut Intel, Fudge tak ingin kau dilatih bertarung.
Combat?
Bertarung?
What does he think, we're forming some sort of wizard army?
Dia pikir kita membentuk tentara penyihir?
That's exactly what he thinks.
Itu yang dia pikir.
That Dumbledore is assembling his own forces to take on the Ministry.
Bahwa Dumbledore sedang membentuk laskar untuk merebut Kementerian.
He’s becoming more paranoid by the minute.
Dia makin lama makin paranoid.
The others wouldn’t want me telling you this, Harry...
Orde melarangku memberitahu kau ini, Harry...
...but things aren't going at all well with the Order.
...tetapi keadaan Orde kurang beres.
Fudge is blocking the truth at every turn...
Fudge tak hentinya menutupi kebenaran...
...and these disappearances are just how it started before.
...dan banyaknya orang hilang itu persis seperti awalnya dahulu.
Voldemort is on the move.
Voldemort sudah bergerak.
Well, what can we do?
Apa yang bisa kita lakukan?
Someone's coming.
Ada yang datang.
I'm sorry I can't be of more help.
Maaf aku tak membantu lebih banyak.
But for now, at least, it looks like you're on your own.
Setidaknya sementara ini kau harus melawan mereka sendiri.
He really is out there, isn’t he?
Voldemort bisa menyerang lagi?
We've got to be able to defend ourselves.
Kita harus bisa mempertahankan diri.
And if Umbridge refuses to teach us how, we need someone who will.
Jika Umbridge tak mau mengajari, kita cari yang mau.
Harry.
Harry.
This is mad. Who'd wanna be taught by me?
Gila! Siapa yang mau kuajari?
I'm a nutter, remember?
Aku ini sinting, ingat?
Look on the bright side: you can’t be any worse than old toad face.
Tetapi kau tak mungkin lebih buruk dari si muka kodok.
-Thanks, Ron. -I'm here for you, mate.
-Terima kasih, Ron. -Aku di belakangmu, Kawan.
Who's supposed to be meeting us, then?
Siapa lagi yang mau kuajar?
Just a couple of people.
Hanya beberapa anak.
Lovely spot.
Tempat bagus.
Thought it would be safer off the beaten track.
Lebih aman di tempat terpencil.
Matey, come back here.
Matey, kembali ke sini.
Hi.
Hai.
So you all know why we're here.
Kalian tahu mengapa kita di sini.
We need a teacher.
Kita perlu guru.
A proper teacher.
Guru ahli.
One who's had experience defending themselves against the Dark Arts.
Yang berpengalaman bertahan terhadap Sihir Hitam.
-Why?
-Mengapa?
Because You-Know-Who's back, you tosspot.
Karena Kau-Tahu-Siapa kembali, Bodoh.
-So he says. -So Dumbledore says.
-Itu kata dia. -Juga kata Dumbledore.
So Dumbledore says because he says.
Kata Dumbledore karena kata dia.
The point is, where's the proof?
Mana buktinya?
If Potter could tell us more about how Diggory got killed....
Coba Potter mau cerita bagaimana Diggory terbunuh.
I'm not gonna talk about Cedric, so if that’s why you’re here, clear out now.
Aku tidak mau. Jika itu alasan kalian kemari, pergi saja.
Come on, Hermione. They're here because they think I'm some sort of freak.
Ayo pergi, Hermione. Mereka datang hanya karena aku aneh.
Is it true you can produce a Patronus Charm?
Benarkah kau bisa melakukan Mantera Patronus?
Yes.
Ya.
I’ve seen it.
Pernah kulihat dia melakukannya.
Blimey, Harry. I didn’t know you could do that.
Astaga, tak kusangka.
And he killed a basilisk, with the sword in Dumbledore’s office.
Dia bunuh monster Basilisk pakai pedang di ruang Dumbledore.
It’s true.
Benar.
Third year, he fought off about a hundred Dementors at once.
Tahun ke-3, dia lawan ratusan Dementor.
Last year, he really did fight off You-Know-Who in the flesh.
Tahun yang lalu dia bertarung lawan Kau-Tahu-Siapa sendiri.
Wait.
Tunggu.
Look, it all sounds great when you say it like that...
Terdengar hebat jika kau ceritakan seperti itu...
...but the truth is, most of that was just luck.
...Sebenarnya sebagian besar hanya keberuntungan.
I didn’t know what I was doing half the time. I nearly always had help.
Aku tak tahu persis apa yang kulakukan, aku selalu dibantu.
-He’s just being modest. -No, Hermione, I’m not.
-Dia hanya merendah. -Tidak, Hermione, itu sebenarnya.
Facing this stuff in real life is not like school.
Gunakan sihir di dunia nyata, tak seperti di sekolah.
In school, if you make a mistake, you can just try again tomorrow.
Di sekolah, jika salah, bisa dicoba lagi besok.
But out there...
Di dunia nyata...
...when you're a second away from being murdered...
.. jika kita nyaris terbunuh...
...or watching a friend die tight before your eyes....
...atau melihat teman mati di hadapan kita...
You don’t know what that’s like.
Kau tak tahu betapa ngerinya.
You're right, Harry, we don't.
Kau benar, kami tak tahu.
That’s why we need your help.
Sebab itu perlu bantuanmu.
Because if we're going to have any chance at beating...
Karena jika kita berpeluang mengalahkan...
...Voldemort....
...Voldemort....
He’s really back.
Dia sungguh kembali.
Right. First we need to find a place to practice...
Harus ada tempat berlatih...
... where Umbridge won't find out.
...yang takkan ketahuan Umbridge.
-The Shrieking Shack. -It’s too small.
-Shrieking Shack. -Terlalu kecil.
-Forbidden Forest? -Not bloody likely.
-Hutan Terlarang. -Tidak mungkin.
Harry, what happens if Umbridge does find out?
Jika ketahuan Umbridge?
Who cares?
Tak jadi soal.
I mean, it’s sort of exciting, isn’t it, breaking the rules?
Pokoknya seru 'kan, bisa melanggar aturan!
Who are you and what have you done with Hermione?
Siapa kau? Kau apakan Hermione yang asli?
Anyway, at least we know one positive thing that came from today.
Setidaknya kita tahu satu hal positif dari hari ini.
What's that?
Apa?
Cho couldn't take her eyes off you, could she?
Cho tak bisa alihkan matanya dari kau, ya?
Right. Over the next few days, we should each come up...
Beberapa hari lagi, semua harus punya usul...
..-with a couple of possibilities of places we can practice.
...tempat mana yang tepat untuk berlatih.
We've got to make sure, wherever it is, there’s no chance she can find us.
Harus dipastikan di mana pun itu, takkan ketahuan Umbridge.
Will do, Harry.
Baik, Harry.
All student organizations are henceforth disbanded.
Semua organisasi siswa sejak saat ini dilarang.
Any student in noncompliance will be expelled.
Siswa yang melanggar akan dikeluarkan dari sekolah.
Watch where you're going, Longbottom.
Lihat jalanmu, Longbottom.
You've done it, Neville. You found the Room of Requirement.
Kau berhasil, Neville. Kau temukan Kamar Kebutuhan.
The what?
Apa?
It’s also known as the Come and Go Room.
Alias Ruang Datang dan Pergi.
The Room of Requirement only appears when a person has real need of it.
Kamar Kebutuhan hanya muncul jika diperlukan.
And it's always equipped for the seeker’s needs.
Selalu dilengkapi kebutuhan pencarinya.
So say you really needed the toilet....
Jika kita perlu WC?
Charming, Ronald. But, yes, that is the general idea.
Gagasan bagus, Ronald. Ya, semua yang dibutuhan.
It’s brilliant. It’s like Hogwarts wants us to fight back.
Bantuan bagus. Sepertinya Hogwarts ingin kita melakukan perlawanan.
Expelliarmus.
Expelliarmus.
I'm hopeless.
Aku tak ada harapan.
You're just flourishing your wand too much. Try it like this. Expelliarmus.
Hanya terlalu keras melambaikannya. Coba begini. Expelliarmus!
You will please copy the approved text four times...
Salin empat kali teks yang disetujui...
...to ensure maximum retention.
...untuk memastikan kalian ingat.
-There will be no need to talk. -No need to think’s more like it.
-Tak perlu bicara! -Tak perlu berpikir, lebih tepat.
-Expelliarmus. -Wands away.
-Expelliarmus. -Simpan tongkatmu!
Stunning is one of the most useful spells in your arsenal.
Mantera bius paling berguna.
It's a wizard’s bread and butter, really.
Itu senjata bertahan yang utama.
So come on, then, Nigel. Give it your best shot.
Jadi, ayo Nigel, tunjukkan kemampuanmu.
Stupefy!
Stupefy!
Good. Not bad at all, Nigel. Well done.
Bagus. Tidak buruk, Nigel. Bagus sekali.
Don’t worry. I'll go easy on you.
Aku akan pelan-pelan.
Thanks, Ronald.
Terima kasih, Ronald.
-Come on, Ron.
-Ayo, Ron.
-You can do it.
-Kau bisa.
-One Sickle. -You're on.
-Bertaruh satu sikel. -Jadi.
Stupefy.
Stupefy.
-Thank you. -Shut up.
-Terima kasih. -Diam, kau.
Il let her do that. It's good manners, isn’t it?
Dia kubiarkan lakukan itu. Begitu etiket yang baik,'kan?
It was completely intentional.
Memang disengaja.
Up you come. Would you like a cup of tea?
Ayo naik. Mau minum teh?
Now, focus on a fixed point and try again.
Fokus pada satu benda diam lalu coba lagi.
Expelliarmus.
Expelliarmus.
Very good. Keep your concentration.
Bagus sekali. Konsentrasi terus.
Great.
Bagus.
A little higher.
Lebih tinggi sedikit.
I'm okay. I’m okay.
Aku tidak apa-apa.
-Stupefy.
-Stupefy.
Those wishing to join the Inquisitorial Squad for extra credit...
Yang mau masuk Regu Inkuisitor untuk mendapat nilai tambahan...
. .-May sign up in the high inquisitor's office.
...bisa mendaftar di kantor Inkuisitor Agung.
Diminuendo.
Diminuendo.
Working hard is important, but there’s something that matters even more:
Penting kerja keras, tetapi ada yang lebih penting.
Believing in yourself.
Yaitu percaya diri.
-Expelliarmus. -Levicorpus. Got it.
-Expelliarmus. -Levicorpus. Bisa.
Think of it this way.
Pikir begini.
Every great wizard in history has started out...
Semua penyihir besar awalnya...
..as nothing more than what we are now: students.
...tak jauh beda dengan kita sekarang, cuma siswa.
If they can do it, why not us?
Jika mereka bisa berhasil, mengapa kita tidak?
-Stupefy. -Expelliarmus.
-Stupefy. -Expelliarmus.
Expelliarmus.
Expelliarmus.
Reducto.
Reducto.
-Expelliarmus.
-Expelliarmus.
Expelliarmus.
Expelliarmus.
Fantastic, Neville. Well done, man.
Menakjubkan, Neville. Bagus.
So that’s it for this lesson.
Sekian pelajaran kita.
Now, we're not gonna be meeting again until after the holidays.
Kita takkan jumpa lagi sampai akhir liburan.
So just keep practicing on your own as best you can.
Berlatih sendiri terus sebaik mungkin.
And well done, everyone. Great, great work.
Bagus, Semua. Kalian berlatih bagus sekali.
Well done, mate.
Bagus, Kawan.
Thanks.
Terima kasih.
See you after Christmas.
Sampai jumpa setelah Natal.
See you in the Common Room, Harry.
Bertemu di Ruang Bersama, Harry.
-Thanks a lot, Harry. -No worries.
-Terima kasih banyak, Harry. -Sama-sama.
-Thank you so much. -Not at all. Merry Christmas.
-Terima kasih banyak. -Sama-sama. Selamat Natal.
-Thank you, Harry. -Thank you. Merry Christmas.
-Terima kasih, Harry. -Terima kasih. Selamat Natal.
-Merry Christmas. -Have a good Christmas.
-Selamat Natal.
-Have a great Christmas, Luna. -We've been thinking.
-Selamat Natal. Luna. -Kami berpikir, Harry.
We could always slip Umbridge some Puking Pastilles.
Masukkan Pastilles Pemuntah ke minuman Umbridge.
Or Fever Fudge. They give you massive, pus-filled boils--
Atau Manisan Meriang. Biar dia bisulan--
Sounds great, guys. Would you excuse me?
Gagasan bagus. Aku pergi dulu,ya?
Are you all right? ! heard Umbridge gave you a rough time the other day.
Kau baik-baik saja? Kudengar Umbridge membuatmu susah kemarin.
Yeah. I’m okay.
Aku baik-baik saja.
Anyway, it’s worth it.
Bagaimanapun, itu setimpal.
It’s just, learning all this...
Hanya saja, mempelajari mantera pertahanan...
...makes me wonder whether, if he'd known it....
...membuatku berpikir, andaikan Cedric tahu mantera itu....
Cedric did know this stuff.
Cedric tahu mantera pertahanan.
He was really good.
Dia penyihir handal.
It’s just, Voldemort was better.
Tetapi Voldemort lebih handal.
You're a really good teacher, Harry.
Kau guru yang baik, Harry.
I’ve never been able to stun anything before.
Tadinya aku tak pernah berhasil memingsankan apapun.
Mistletoe.
Daun Mistletoe.
Probably full of Nargles, though.
Tetapi itu sarang Nargle.
What are Nargles?
Apa Nargle itu?
No idea.
Aku tidak tahu.
Well, how was it?
Bagaimana ciumannya?
Wet.
Basah.
I mean, she was sort of crying.
Soalnya dia menangis.
That bad at it, are you?
Seburuk itukah ciumanmu?
I'm sure Harry’s kissing was more than satisfactory.
Aku yakin ciuman Harry lebih dari memuaskan.
Cho spends half her time crying these days.
Cho sering menangis kini.
You'd think a bit of snogging would cheer her up.
Kalian pikir ciuman akan menghiburnya.
Don't you understand how she must be feeling?
Kau tak memahami perasaannya?
Well, obviously she’s feeling sad about Cedric...
Jelas dia sedih ingat Cedric...
..and confused about liking Harry and guilty about kissing him...
...bingung karena menyukai Harry, merasa bersalah menciumnya...
...conflicted because Umbridge might sack her mum from the Ministry...
...dan galau karena Umbridge mau memecat ibunya dari Kementerian...
..and frightened of failing her OWLs because she’s worrying about everything.
...dan takut tak lulus OWL karena pikirannya penuh urusan lain.
One person couldn't feel all that. They'd explode.
Satu orang tak mungkin merasakan semua itu. Bisa meledak.
Just because you've got the emotional range of a teaspoon....
Karena kau tak mampu merasakan semua hal.
Harry.
Harry.
Voldemort may be after something.
Voldemort mungkin mengincar sesuatu.
Something he didn't have last time.
Sesuatu yang tak didapatnya dulu.
Harry.
Harry.
In the dream, were you standing next to the victim...
Di mimpimu kau berdiri di sisi korban...
...or looking down at the scene?
...atau melihat TKP?
Neither. It was like I....
Tidak dua-duanya. Saya sepertinya....
Will you please just tell me what's happening?
Profesor, apa yang terjadi?
Everard, Arthur's on guard duty tonight.
Malam ini Arthur yang jaga.
Make sure he’s found by the right people.
Pastikan dia ditemukan oleh anggota Orde.
-Sir. -Phineas.
-Pak. -Phineas.
You must go to your portrait at Grimmauld Place.
Pergi ke potretmu di Grimmauld Place.
Tell them that Arthur Weasley is gravely injured...
Beritahu mereka, Arthur Weasley luka parah...
..and his children will be arriving there soon by Portkey.
...anak-anaknya akan segera tiba di sana pakai Portkey.
They've got him, Albus. It was close, but they think he'll make it.
Mereka selamatkan dia, nyaris mati, tetapi akan selamat.
What's more, the Dark Lord failed to acquire it.
Pangeran Kegelapan gagal mendapatkan bola itu.
Oh, thank goodness. Next we need to--
Syukurlah. Kita perlu--
Look at me!
Pandang aku!
What’s happening to me?
Apa yang terjadi padaku?
You wished to see me, headmaster?
Mau bertemu saya, Pak Kepala Sekolah?
Oh, Severus. I’m afraid we can’t wait. Not even till the morning.
Oh, Severus. Kita tak bisa menunggu. Besok pagi pun sudah terlambat.
Otherwise, we'll all be vulnerable.
Jika tidak, kita semua takkan berdaya.
It appears there’s a connection...
Agaknya ada kaitan...
...between the Dark Lord’s mind and your own.
...antara pikiran Pangeran Kegelapan dengan pikiranmu.
Whether he is, as yet, aware of this connection is, for the moment, unclear.
Tak jelas apa dia tahu tentang kaitan itu.
Pray he remains ignorant.
Harap saja dia belum tahu.
You mean, if he knows about it, then...
Jika dia tahu...
-...he'll be able to read my mind? -Read it, control it...
-....dia dapat membaca pikiran saya? -Membaca dan mengendalikannya.
...unhinge it.
Membuatmu jadi gila.
In the past, it was often the Dark Lord's pleasure...
Dulu, Pangeran Kegelapan senang...
...to invade the minds of his victims...
...memasuki pikiran korbannya...
..creating visions designed to torture them into madness.
...menciptakan bayangan yang menyiksa korbannya sampai jadi gila.
Only after extracting the last exquisite ounce of agony...
Hanya setelah siksaannya sudah tak tertahankan lagi...
..-only when he had them literally begging for death, would he finally...
...sampai korbannya minta mati, barulah akan...
..-kill them.
...dia bunuh.
Used properly, the power of Occlumency...
Jika digunakan dengan tepat, kekuatan Occlumency...
..-Will help shield you from access or influence.
...akan membentengimu dari pengaruh.
In these lessons, I will attempt to penetrate your mind.
Di pelajaran ini akan kucoba menembus pikiranmu.
You will attempt to resist.
Harus kau upayakan menangkis.
Prepare yourself.
Bersiaplah.
Legilimens.
Legilimens.
Concentrate, Potter. Focus.
Konsentrasi, Potter. Fokus.
Ho, ho, ho. Merry Christmas.
Ho, ho, ho. Selamat Natal.
Here we go.
Ayo semua!
Daddy's back.
Ayah pulang dari rumah sakit!
Sit down, everybody, sit down. That's it. Now, presents.
Semua duduk, duduk. Begitu. Sekarang hadiah Natalnya.
-And a nice big box for Ron. -Big box for you. And....
-Dus besar untuk Ron. -Dus besar untuk kau.
Fred and George. Come on, open up.
Fred dan George. Ayo dibuka.
-l want to see your faces. -Yes.
-Aku mau lihat wajah kalian. -Ya.
-Try it on. -Thanks, Mum. It's perfect.
-Coba dipakai. -Bagus, Ibu.
-Just what he wanted, actually. -Yeah. Right. Thanks, Mum.
-Seperti yang dia inginkan. -Betul. Terima kasih, Bu.
Come on, then, everybody. Let's clear this away.
Ayo semua, keluar lewat sini.
Oh, Harry, Harry.
Oh, Harry, Harry.
There you are.
Kau datang.
-Happy Christmas. -Thank you.
-Selamat Natal. -Terima kasih.
-Lovely to have you with us.
-Senang kau bersama kami.
Now, Daddy. Pass that to Daddy.
Berikan itu pada Ayah.
-Thank you. -Has everybody got?
-Terima kasih. -Semua sudah dapat?
Fred? George?
Fred? George?
-Hermione. -A Christmas toast.
-Hermione. -Sulangan Natal!
To Mr. Harry Potter...
Untuk Tn. Harry Potter...
...without whom I would not be here.
...karena dia, Ayah masih hidup.
-Harry.
-Harry.
Harry.
Harry.
That is delicious. I shall be needing some more of that.
Enak sekali. Masih mau tambah.
Daddy, don't forget last Christmas.
Ayah, jangan lupa Natal yang lalu.
I can’t understand why you don't want to wear it, Ronald.
Aku tak mengerti mengapa kau tak mau memakainya.
l look like a bloody idiot, that’s why.
Karena aku tampak bodoh.
No more than usual, Ron.
Tak lebih dari biasanya.
I don't know why....
Mengapa kau tak lebih mempercayai selera ibumu!
Nasty brat, standing there as bold as brass.
Anak brengsek yang berdiri dengan angkuhnya itu.
Harry Potter, the boy who stopped the Dark Lord.
Harry Potter, anak yang melawan Pangeran Kegelapan.
Friend of Mudbloods and blood-traitors alike.
Kawan para Darah Lumpur dan para pengkhianat darah.
-lf my poor mistress only knew.... -Kreacher!
-Kalau saja Nyonyaku tahu.... -Kreacher!
That's enough of your bile. Away with you!
Cukup menuduh! Pergi!
Of course, master.
Baik, Tuanku.
Kreacher lives to serve the noble house of Black.
Kreacher hidup untuk mengabdi keluarga Black.
Sorry about that.
Maaf soal itu.
He never was very pleasant, even when I was a boy.
Dia tak menyenangkan, walau saat aku kecil.
Not to me, anyway.
Tidak bagiku.
What, you grew up here?
Apa kau dibesarkan di sini?
This is my parents’ house.
Ini rumah orangtuaku.
I offered it to Dumbledore as headquarters for the Order.
Kutawarkan pada Dumbledore jadi Markas Orde Phoenix.
About the only useful thing I've been able to do.
Hanya itu hal berguna yang bisa kulakukan.
This is the Black family tree.
Ini pohon keluarga Black.
My deranged cousin.
Sepupuku yang gila.
I hated the lot of them.
Kubenci mereka semua.
My parents with their pure-blood mania.
Orangtuaku yang terobsesi darah murni mereka.
My mother did that after I ran away.
Itu dilakukan ibuku setelah aku kabur dari rumah.
Charming woman.
Wanita menarik.
I was 16.
Saat itu umurku 16 tahun.
Where did you go?
Kau kabur ke mana?
Round your dad's.
Ke ayahmu.
l was always welcome at the Potters’.
Aku selalu diterima di rumah keluarga Potter.
l see him so much in you, Harry.
Kulihat begitu banyak sifat ayahmu pada dirimu.
You are so very much alike.
Kalian begitu serupa.
I'm not so sure.
Aku tak begitu yakin.
Sirius, when I was....
Sirius, saat aku....
When I saw Mr. Weasley attacked, I wasn't just watching.
Saat lihat Tn. Weasley diserang, aku bukan hanya melihat.
l was the snake.
Kualami serangan itu dari pandangan mata ular itu.
And afterwards, in Dumbledore’s office...
Setelah itu, di kantor Dumbledore...
...there was a moment when I wanted to--
...ada sesaat aku ingin--
This connection between me and Voldemort.
Kaitan antara aku dan Voldemort.
What if the reason for it is that 1 am becoming more like him?
Bagaimana jika semua itu karena aku makin menjadi seperti dia?
I just feel so angry all the time.
Aku hanya merasa begitu marah sepanjang waktu.
And what if, after everything that I’ve been through...
Bagaimana andai setelah segala yang kualami...
...something’s gone wrong inside me? What if I'm becoming bad?
...ada yang tak beres dalam diriku. Aku jadi jahat?
l want you to listen to me very carefully, Harry.
Dengarkan aku baik-baik, Harry.
You're not a bad person.
Kau bukan orang jahat.
You're a very good person who bad things have happened to.
Kau orang yang sangat baik yang mengalami hal-hal buruk.
You understand?
Kau mengerti?
Besides, the world isn’t split into good people and Death Eaters.
Lagipula dunia tak hanya dihuni orang baik dan Pelahap Maut.
We've all got both light and dark inside of us.
Sisi baik atau jahat ada di dalam diri kita semua.
What matters is the part we choose to act on.
Yang penting adalah yang mana yang kita pilih.
That's who we really are.
Itulah kita yang sebenarnya.
Harry, time to go.
Harry, saatnya pergi.
When all this is over, we'll be a proper family.
Jika semua ini sudah berlalu, kita akan jadi satu keluarga.
You'll see.
Lihat saja.
Come on.
Sungguh?
Really?
Benarkah?
Harry. Harry.
Harry. Harry.
Hagrid’s back.
Hagrid kembali.
I'm sorry.
Maafkan aku.
I will say this one last time.
Kutanya untuk terakhir kali.
I'm ordering you to tell me where you've been.
Kau dari mana selama ini?
Il told you. I've been away for me health.
Sudah kukatakan, aku pergi demi kesehatanku.
-Your health? -Yeah. Bit of fresh air, you know.
-Kesehatanmu? -Ya. Aku perlu udara segar.
Oh, yes. As gamekeeper, fresh air must be difficult to come by.
Oh ya. Sebagai pengawas hutan pasti sulit dapatkan itu.
If l were you, I shouldn't get too used to being back.
Jangan terlalu terbiasa untuk datang dan pergi.
In fact, ! mightn’t bother unpacking at all.
Kau tak perlu membongkar barangmu.
This is top-secret, right?
Ini sangat rahasia, mengerti?
Dumbledore sent me to parley with the giants.
Aku dikirim Dumbledore untuk berunding dengan bangsa raksasa.
Giants?
Raksasa?
You found them?
Kau temukan?
Well, they're not that hard to find, to be perfectly honest. They’re so big, see?
Tak terlalu sukar menemukan mereka. Mereka begitu besar.
I tried to convince them to join the cause.
Mereka kubujuk untuk bergabung.
But I wasn’t the only one that was trying to win them over.
Tetapi bukan hanya aku yang membujuk mereka.
-Death Eaters? -Yes.
-Pelahap Maut? -Ya.
Trying to persuade them to join You-Know-Who.
Mereka dibujuk gabung dengan Kau-Tahu-Siapa.
-Did they? -l gave them Dumbledore’s message.
-Mereka bergabung? -Kuberikan surat Dumbledore.
Suppose some of them remember he was friendly to them. I suppose.
Mungkin mereka masih ingat keramahannya pada mereka.
And they did this to you?
Ini perbuatan mereka?
Not exactly, no.
Bukan.
Oh, go on, you have it, then, you dozy dog.
Yah, makan saja itu, anjing pemalas.
It’s changing out there.
Keadaan berubah di sana.
Just like last time.
Seperti saat itu.
There's a storm coming, Harry.
Akan ada badai, Harry.
We'd all best be ready when she does.
Harus sudah siap saat itu datang.
We have confirmed that 10 high-security prisoners...
Dipastikan sepuluh narapidana paling berbahaya...
...in the early hours of yesterday evening did escape.
...kabur awal petang kemarin.
And of course, the Muggle prime minister has been alerted to the danger.
Tentu Perdana Menteri Muggle sudah diperingatkan soal ini.
We strongly suspect...
Diduga keras...
...that the breakout was engineered...
...pelarian ini diotaki oleh...
...by a man with personal experience in escaping from Azkaban...
...orang yang berpengalaman kabur dari Azkaban...
..-notorious mass murderer Sirius Black...
...pembunuh masal terkenal Sirius Black...
...cousin of escapee Bellatrix Lestrange.
...sepupu buronan Bellatrix Lestrange.
Dumbledore warned Fudge this could happen.
Dumbledore peringatkan Fudge ini bisa terjadi.
He’s gonna get us all killed just because he can't face the truth.
Dia akan membunuh kita karena dia tak bisa menghadapi kenyataan.
Harry.
Harry.
I wanted to apologize.
Maafkan aku.
Now even me mum says the Prophet's version of things don’t add up.
Ibuku pun bilang, versi The Prophet tak masuk akal.
So, what I’m really trying to say is that I believe you.
Yang kucoba katakan, yaitu aku percaya padamu.
Neville?
Neville?
Fourteen years ago...
Empat belas tahun yang lalu...
...a Death Eater named Bellatrix Lestrange...
...Pelahap Maut bernama Bellatrix Lestrange...
...used a Cruciatus Curse on my parents.
...gunakan Kutukan Cruciatus terhadap orangtuaku.
She tortured them for information...
Mereka disiksa untuk dapatkan informasi...
...but they never gave in.
...tetapi mereka tak menyerah.
I'm quite proud to be their son.
Aku bangga jadi anak mereka.
But I’m not sure I'm ready for everyone to know just yet.
Tetapi aku belum siap semua tahu tentang orangtuaku.
We're gonna make them proud, Neville. That's a promise.
Orangtuamu akan kita buat bangga padamu, Neville.
Make it a powerful memory, the happiest you can remember.
Pikirkan saat paling bahagia yang bisa kauingat.
Allow it to fill you up. Keep trying, Seamus.
Penuhi pikiranmu dengan itu. Coba terus, Seamus.
George, your turn now.
George, sekarang giliranmu.
Expecto Patronum.
Expecto Patronum.
A full-bodied Patronus is the most difficult to produce...
Patronus yang seakan hidup, paling sukar menciptakannya...
...but shield forms can also be equally useful against a variety of opponents.
...tetapi menciptakan perisai pun berguna terhadap berbagai lawan.
Wow, that was really good.
Bagus sekali.
Fantastic, Ginny.
Hebat, Ginny!
Just remember, your Patronus can only protect you for as long as you stay focused.
Patronusmu hanya melindungi selama kau fokus.
So focus, Luna.
Jadi fokuslah, Luna.
Think of the happiest thing you can.
Ingat saat terbahagiamu.
Expecto Patronum.
Expecto Patronum.
-I'm trying. -l know. It’s good.
-Kucoba. -Aku tahu. Itu bagus.
This is really advanced stuff, guys. You're doing so well.
Ini sihir pertahanan tercanggih. Kalian lakukan baik sekali.
Expecto Patronum.
Expecto Patronum.
Pll make short work of this.
Akan kuhentikan segera omong kosong ini.
Bombarda Maxima.
Bombarda Maxima.
Get them.
Tangkap mereka!
Been watching them for weeks.
Berminggu-minggu kuawasi.
And see, "Dumbledore’s Army”...
Lihat, “Laskar Dumbledore"...
...proof of what I've been telling you tight from the beginning, Cornelius.
...bukti yang kukatakan padamu sejak mula, Cornelius.
All your fear-mongering about You-Know-Who...
Intimidasimu tentang Kau-Tahu-Siapa...
...-never fooled us for a minute.
... tak memperdaya kami.
We saw your lies for what they were:
Kami tahu kebohonganmu:
A smokescreen for your bid to seize control of the Ministry.
Tabir-asapmu untuk merebut kekuasaan di Kementerian.
Naturally.
Tentu.
No, professor. He had nothing to do with it. It was me.
Tidak! Profesor tak tahu apa-apa! Ini perbuatanku!
Most noble of you, Harry, to shield me, but as has been pointed out...
Mulia sekali, Harry, melindungiku, tetapi seperti terlihat...
...the parchment clearly says “Dumbledore’s Army," not "Potter's."
...di dokumen itu tertulis "Laskar Dumbledore" bukan "Potter."
l instructed Harry to form this organization.
Kuperintahkan Harry membentuk organisasi ini.
And I, and I alone, am responsible for its activities.
Dan hanya aku yang bertanggung-jawab atas semua ini.
Dispatch an owl to the Daily Prophet.
Kirim burung ke "Daily Prophet."
If we hurry, we should still make the morning edition.
Masih sempat masuk Edisi Pagi.
Dawlish, Shacklebolt, you will escort Dumbledore...
Dawlish, Shacklebolt, kawal Dumbledore...
...to Azkaban...
...ke Azkaban...
...to await trial for conspiracy and sedition.
...untuk menunggu diadili atas tuduhan berkomplot dan menghasut.
I thought we might hit this little snag.
Sudah kuduga akan kita temui masalah kecil ini.
You seem to be laboring under the delusion that I’m going to--
Salah jika kalian berpikir aku akan--
What was the phrase?
Apa istilahnya?
--come quietly.
Menurut saja.
Well, I can tell you this:
Tetapi yang jelas.
I have no intention of going to Azkaban.
Aku tak berniat pergi ke Azkaban.
Enough of this.
Cukup ini.
Take him.
Ayo bawa dia!
Well, you may not like him, minister...
Kau mungkin tak menyukainya, Menteri...
...but you can't deny...
...tetapi tak bisa kau bantah...
...Dumbledore has got style.
...Dumbledore itu punya gaya.
Boys and girls are not permitted to be within eight inches of each other.
Siswa dilarang saling berdekatan sampai 8 inci.
Those wishing to join the inquisitorial Squad for extra credit....
Siswa yang ingin menjadi anggota Regu Inkuisitor untuk mendapat nilai lebih....
Students will be submitted to questioning about suspected illicit activities.
Siswa yang dicurigai terlibat kegiatan terlarang akan diinterogasi.
Any student in noncompliance will be expelled.
Siswa yang melanggar akan dikeluarkan.
Harry.
Harry.
You did everything you could. No one could win against that old hag.
Sudah kaulakukan segalanya. Tak mungkin menang lawan nenek itu.
Even Dumbledore didn’t see this coming.
Dumbledore pun tak menyangka.
Harry, if it's anyone’s fault, it’s ours.
Harry, yang salah kami.
Yeah, we talked you into it.
Kami paksa kau mengajari kami.
Yeah, but I agreed.
Tetapi aku mau.
I tried so hard to help, and all it’s done is make things worse.
Aku berusaha keras membantu, tapi malah memperburuk keadaan.
Anyway, that doesn’t matter anymore.
Tetapi itu bukan soal lagi.
Because I don't want to play anymore. All it does is make you care too much.
Aku tak mau bertarung lagi. Hanya membuatmu memikirkanku.
And the more you care, the more you have to lose.
Makin memikirkanku, makin sulit menerima kekalahan.
-So maybe it’s just better to.... -To what?
-Jadi mungkin lebih baik.... -Apa?
To go it alone.
Kulakukan sendiri.
Hagrid.
Hagrid.
Any idea where he’s taking us?
Kita mau dibawa ke mana?
Hagrid, why can’t you just tell us?
Hagrid, mengapa tak kaukatakan saja?
I've never seen the centaurs so riled.
Tak pernah kulihat para Centaur begitu gelisah.
And they're dangerous at the best of times.
Saat tenang pun berbahaya.
The Ministry restricts their territory much more...
Kementerian membatasi lagi daerahnya...
... they'll have a full uprising on their hands.
...mereka bisa berontak.
Hagrid, what's going on?
Hagrid, ada apa?
I'm sorry to be so mysterious, you three.
Maaf aku begitu berahasia pada kalian.
I wouldn't be bothering you at all with it, but with Dumbledore gone...
Aku mau katakan semua, tetapi dengan hilangnya Dumbledore...
.. [Il likely be getting the sack any day now.
...setiap saat aku bisa dipecat.
And I just couldn't leave without telling someone about him.
Tetapi aku tak bisa pergi tanpa beritahu seseorang tentang dia.
Grawpy.
Grawpy.
Down here, you great buffoon.
Aku di bawah sini, Bodoh.
Brought you some company.
Kubawakan teman untukmu.
I couldn't just leave him, because--
Dia tak bisa kutinggal karena--
Because he’s my brother.
Karena dia saudaraku.
Blimey.
Astaga.
Well, half brother, really.
Tepatnya saudara satu ibu.
He’s completely harmless, just like I said. Little high-spirited, is all.
Dia tak berbahaya, seperti kataku. Hanya sedikit bersemangat.
-Grawpy, that is not polite. -Hagrid, do something.
-Grawpy, itu tidak sopan! -Hagrid, lakukan sesuatu!
We talked about this. You do not grab, do you?
Ini sudah kita bahas. Jangan mencekal orang.
That's your new friend, Hermione.
Itu teman barumu. Hermione.
Grawpy.
Grawpy.
Grawp.
Grawp.
Put me down.
Turunkan aku!
Now.
Sekarang juga!
You all right?
Kau baik-baik saja?
Fine.
Aku tak apa-apa.
Just needs a firm hand, is all.
Dia hanya perlu disiplin.
I think you've got an admirer.
Kurasa dia pengagummu.
You just stay away from her, all right?
Jauhi saja dia, ya?
He gets his own food and all.
Dia cari makan sendiri.
It's company he'll be needing when I'm gone.
Yang dia butuhkan teman jika aku pergi.
You will look after him, won't you?
Kau mau mengunjunginya, 'kan?
I'm the only family he’s got.
Hanya aku keluarganya.
Feeling sentimental?
Merasa sedih?
-That’s private. -Not to me.
-Itu kenangan pribadi. -Bagiku tidak.
And not to the Dark Lord, if you don't improve.
Bagi Pangeran Kegelapan pun tidak jika tak kaulindungi pikiranmu.
Every memory he has access to is a weapon he can use against you.
Kau langsung kalah jika dia bisa memasuki pikiranmu.
You won't last two seconds if he invades your mind.
Tiap kenanganmu yang terbaca oleh dia jadi senjata melawanmu.
You're just like your father.
Kau persis ayahmu.
Lazy, arrogant.
Malas dan angkuh.
-Don’t say a word against my father. -Weak.
-Jangan menjelekkan ayahku! -Lemah.
-I’m not weak. -Then prove it.
-Aku tidak lemah. -Buktikan.
Control your emotions.
Kendalikan emosimu.
Discipline your mind.
Disiplinkan pikiranmu.
Legilimens.
Legilimens.
Harry.
Harry.
Sirius.
Sirius.
fi may vomit.
Rasanya mau muntah.
Stop it.
Hentikan!
Is this what you call control?
Ini kau sebut kendali emosi?
We've been at it for hours. If I could just rest.
Sudah berjam-jam. Aku mau istirahat.
The Dark Lord isn't resting.
Pangeran Kegelapan tak pernah istirahat.
You and Black, you're two of a kind.
Kau dan Black sama.
Sentimental children forever whining about how bitterly unfair your lives have been.
Anak sentimentil, selalu mengeluh betapa hidupmu tak adil.
Well, it may have escaped your notice, but life isn’t fair.
Tetapi hidup tak adil pada siapapun.
Your blessed father knew that. In fact, he frequently saw to it.
Ayahmu tahu itu. Dia sering berlaku tak adil.
-My father was a great man. -Your father was a swine.
-Ayahku orang hebat! -Ayahmu orang hina.
-Legilimens. -Protego.
-Legilimens. -Protego.
Come on, Moony, Padfoot.
Ayo, Moony, Padfoot.
Snape. Expelliarmus.
Snape. Expelliarmus.
Nice one, James.
Mantera bagus, James.
-Dad. -impedimenta.
-Ayah. -Impedimenta.
Snivellus Greasy.
Snivellus Berminyak.
Right. Who wants to see me take off Snivelly’s trousers?
Siapa mau lihat celana Snivelly kulepas?
Enough.
Cukup.
Your lessons are at an end.
Pelajaranmu berakhir.
[--
Aku--
Get out.
Keluar.
-What's your name? -Michael.
-Siapa namamu? -Michael.
Your hand’s gonna be fine, Michael.
Tanganmu akan baik-baik, Michael.
Yeah. It’s not as bad as it seems. See?
Tak seburuk tampaknya. Lihat.
It’s fading already.
Sudah memudar.
You can hardly see ours anymore, and the pain stops after a while.
Luka kami hampir tak tampak lagi dan sakitnya akan berhenti.
As I told you once before, Mr. Potter...
Seperti kataku dulu, Tn. Potter...
. naughty children deserve to be punished.
...anak nakal patut dihukum.
You know, George...
Kau tahu, George...
...[’ve always felt our futures lay outside the world of academic achievement.
...kurasa masa depan kita tak terkait dengan sekolah.
Fred, I've been thinking exactly the same thing.
Fred, itu pula yang kupikir selama ini.
All right, professor!
Baiklah, Profesor!
Here you go.
Ini dia.
Ready when you are.
Kami siap!
I need that prophecy.
Kubutuhkan ramalan itu.
You'll have to kill me.
Lewati mayatku.
Oh, I will. But first, you will fetch it for me.
Nanti. Ambilkan dulu Ramalan itu untukku.
Crucio.
Crucio.
Sirius.
Sirius.
Harry, are you sure?
Harry, kau yakin?
Il saw it. It’s just like with Mr. Weasley.
Kulihat. Seperti kejadian Tn. Weasley.
It’s the door I’ve been dreaming about.
Pintu yang sama yang kuimpikan selama sebulan ini...
I couldn’t remember where I'd seen it before.
...cuma entah di mana?
Sirius said Voldemort was after something.
Kata Sirius, Voldemort mengincar sesuatu...
Something he didn’t have the last time, in the Department of Mysteries.
...yang dulu tak dia dapatkan, adanya di Departemen Misteri.
Harry, please, just listen.
Harry, tolong, dengarkan saja.
What if Voldemort meant for you to see this?
Bagaimana andai Voldemort sengaja membuatmu melihat ini?
What if he’s only hurting Sirius because he’s trying to get to you?
Dia sakiti Sirius hanya untuk memikatmu lalu menangkapmu?
What if he is? I'm supposed to just let him die?
Bagaimana andai ya? Kubiarkan saja dia mati?
Hermione, he’s the only family I’ve got left.
Hermione, hanya dia keluargaku yang masih hidup.
What do we do?
Apa daya kita?
We'll have to use the Floo Network.
Kita gunakan Jaringan Floo.
Umbridge has the chimneys under surveillance.
Semua cerobong diawasi.
Not all of them.
Tidak semua.
Alohomora.
Alohomora.
Alert the Order if you can.
Peringatkan Orde!
-Are you mental? We're going with you. -It’s too dangerous.
-Gila? Kami ikut kau. -Terlalu berbahaya!
When are you going to get it into your head? We're in this together.
Kapan akan kausadari? Kita berhasil atau tertangkap bersama!
That you are.
Kalian sudah tertangkap.
Caught this one trying to help the Weasley girl.
Dia mau menolong anak perempuan Weasley.
You were going to Dumbledore, weren't you?
Mau menemui Dumbledore, 'kan?
-No. -Liar.
-Tidak. -Pembohong!
-You sent for me, headmistress? -Snape, yes.
-Memanggilku, Ibu Kepala Sekolah? -Snape, ya.
The time has come for answers, whether he wants to give them to me or not.
Tiba saatnya dia menjawab. Dia mau memberikan padaku atau tidak.
Have you brought the Veritaserum?
Kau bawa Veritaserum-nya?
I'm afraid you've used up all my stores interrogating students.
Sudah habis saat menginterogasi para siswa...
The last of it on Miss Chang.
...yang terakhir Nn. Chang.
Unless you wish to poison him--
Kecuali mau meracuninya--
And I assure you, I would have the greatest sympathy if you did.
Dan memang itu sudah seharusnya.
--l cannot help you.
--aku tak bisa menolongmu.
He’s got Padfoot.
Dia sekap Padfoot.
He’s got Padfoot at the place where it’s hidden.
Dia sekap Padfood di tempat yang tersembunyi.
Padfoot? What is Padfoot? Where what is hidden?
Apa itu Padfoot? Disembunyikan di mana?
What is he talking about, Snape?
Apa maksudnya, Snape?
No idea.
Aku tidak tahu.
Very well.
Baiklah.
You give me no choice, Potter.
Kau tak memberiku pilihan, Potter.
As this is an issue of Ministry security...
Karena ini masalah keamanan Kementerian...
...you leave me with...
...kau tak memberiku...
..no alternative.
...pilihan lain.
The Cruciatus Curse ought to loosen your tongue.
Kutukan Cruciatus akan membuatmu bicara.
That's illegal.
Itu terlarang.
What Cornelius doesn't know won't hurt him.
Asal Cornelius tak tahu, tak jadi masalah.
Tell her, Harry!
Katakan, Harry!
Tell me what?
Katakan apa?
Well, if you won't tell her where it is...
Jika tak kaukatakan di mana itu...
- el will,
...akan kukatakan.
Where what is?
Di mana apa?
Dumbledore’s secret weapon.
Senjata rahasia Dumbledore.
How much further?
Berapa jauh lagi?
Not far.
Tidak jauh.
It had to be somewhere students wouldn't find it accidentally.
Di suatu tempat yang takkan ditemukan para siswa.
What are you doing?
Apa yang kaulakukan?
Improvising.
Improvisasi.
Well?
Bagaimana?
Where is this weapon?
Di mana senjata itu?
There isn't one, is there?
Tak ada senjata, 'kan?
You were trying to trick me.
Kau mau memperdayaiku.
You know...
Tahukah...
...L really hate children.
...aku benar-benar benci anak-anak.
You have no business here, centaur. This is a Ministry matter.
Kau tak ada urusan di sini, Centaur. Ini urusan Kementerian.
Lower your weapons.
Turunkan busur dan panahmu.
I warn you, under the law, as creatures of near-human intelligence....
Awas, sebagai makhluk di bawah manusia, menurut hukum....
Protego.
Protego.
How dare you?
Beraninya kau!
Filthy half-breed.
Makhluk campuran menjijikkan!
incarcerous.
Incarcerous.
Please. Please stop it. Please.
Kumohon! Hentikan! Kumohon!
Now, enough. I will have order.
Sudah, cukup! Semua tertib!
You filthy animal.
Binatang menjijikkan!
Do you know who I am?
Kau tahu siapa aku?!
Leave him alone. It’s not his fault.
Biarkan dia! Bukan salah dia!
No, he doesn’t understand.
Dia tidak mengerti!
Potter, do something. Tell them I mean no harm.
Potter, lakukan sesuatu. Katakan aku tak jahat.
I'm sorry, professor.
Maafkan aku, Profesor.
But I must not tell lies.
Aku tidak boleh berbohong.
What are you doing?
Apa-apaan?!
lam Senior Undersecretary Dolores Jane Umbridge.
Aku Asisten Menteri Dolores Jane Umbridge!
Let me go!
Lepaskan aku!
Thank you, Grawp.
Terima kasih, Grawp.
Hermione. Hermione, Sirius.
Hermione. Hermione, Sirius.
-How’'d you get away? -Puking Pastilles. It wasn't pretty.
-Bagaimana kalian bisa lolos? -Permen Pemuntah. Menjijikkan.
Told them I was hungry, wanted some sweets.
Kataku aku ingin permen.
They told me to bugger off and ate the lot themselves.
Tentu mereka makan sendiri semua.
That was clever, Ron.
Kau pintar, Ron.
-Has been known to happen. -It was brilliant.
-Memang. -Pintar.
So how are we getting to London?
Lalu bagaimana cara kita ke London?
Look, it’s not that 1 don’t appreciate everything you've done, all of you...
Bukannya tak kuhargai semua yang telah kalian lakukan.
...but I've got you into enough trouble as it is.
Tetapi kalian sudah cukup kubahayakan.
Dumbledore’s Army's supposed to be about doing something real.
Laskar Dumbledore dibentuk untuk bertarung.
Or was that all just words to you?
Ataukah hanya kata-kata bagimu?
Maybe you don't have to do this all by yourself, mate.
Tak perlu kaulakukan sendiri semuanya, Kawan.
So how are we going to get to London?
Bagaimana kita ke London?
We fly, of course.
Kita terbang, tentu.
Department of Mysteries.
Departemen Misteri.
This is it.
Ini pintu itu.
Ninety-two. Ninety-three.
Sembilan puluh dua. Sembilan puluh tiga.
Ninety-four.
Sembilan puluh empat.
Ninety-five.
Sembilan puluh lima.
-He should be here. -Harry.
-Dia pasti di sini. -Harry.
It’s got your name on it.
Ada namamu.
The one with the power to vanquish the Dark Lord approaches.
Dia yang berkekuatan mengalahkan Pangeran Kegelapan mendekat.
And the Dark Lord shall mark him as his equal...
Akan dihadapi Pangeran sebagai lawan setara...
...but he shall have power the Dark Lord knows not.
...tetapi Pangeran tak tahu kekuatan lawannya.
For neither can live while the other survives.
Karena tak ada yang bisa hidup Jika yang satunya masih hidup.
Harry.
Harry.
Where's Sirius?
Mana Sirius?
You know, you really should learn to tell the difference between dreams...
Belajarlah membedakan antara impian...
...and reality.
...dan kenyataan.
You saw only what the Dark Lord wanted you to see.
Kau lihat hanya yang diinginkan Pangeran kaulihat.
Now, hand me the prophecy.
Serahkan ramalan itu.
If you do anything to us, I'll break it.
Jika kami kausakiti, ini kupecahkan.
He knows how to play.
Dia tahu cara menantang lawan.
Itty, bitty baby.
Bocah lancang.
Potter.
Potter.
Bellatrix Lestrange.
Bellatrix Lestrange.
Neville Longbottom, is it? How's Mum and Dad?
Neville Longbottom, 'kan? Bagaimana Ayah dan Ibu?
Better, now they're about to be avenged.
Lebih baik, dendamnya akan dibalas.
Now, let's everybody just calm down...
Harap semua tetap tenang...
... shall we?
...oke?
All we want is that prophecy.
Kami hanya menginginkan ramalan itu.
Why did Voldemort need me to come and get this?
Mengapa Voldemort ingin aku yang mengambilnya?
You dare speak his name?
Kau berani menyebut namanya!
You filthy half-blood!
Darah-campuran busuk!
It’s all right. He’s just a curious lad, aren't you?
Tak apa-apa. Dia hanya mau tahu, ya 'kan?
Prophecies can only be retrieved by those about whom they are made.
Ramalan itu hanya bisa ditemukan untuk siapa itu dibuat.
Which is lucky for you, really.
Yang untung bagimu, sungguh.
Haven't you always wondered...
Bukankah kau ingin tahu...
...what was the reason for the connection between you and the Dark Lord?
...mengapa ada kaitan antara kau dan Pangeran Kegelapan?
Why he was unable to kill you...
Mengapa dia tak bisa membunuh kau...
...when you were just an infant?
...saat kau masih bayi?
Don't you want to know the secret of your scar?
Tidakkah kau ingin tahu rahasia bekas-lukamu?
All the answers are there, Potter, in your hand.
Semua jawabannya ada di bola ramalan di tanganmu itu, Potter.
All you have to do...
Yang perlu kaulakukan hanyalah...
.. is give it to me.
...berikan itu padaku.
Then I can show you everything.
Lalu akan kuungkap semua padamu.
I've waited 14 years.
Empat belas tahun kutunggu.
I know.
Aku tahu.
I guess I can wait a little longer. Now. Stupefy.
Bisa kutunggu sebentar. Sekarang! Stupefy.
Stupefy.
Stupefy.
Levicorpus.
Levicorpus.
Petrificus Totalus.
Petrificus Totalus.
Well done, Neville.
Bagus, Neville.
Stupefy.
Stupefy.
-Stupefy.
-Stupefy.
Reducto.
Reducto.
Get back to the door.
Mundur ke pintu!
Department of Mysteries. They got that bit right, didn’t they?
Departemen Misteri. Mereka benar, kamar ini tempat bagi misteri.
The voices.
Kudengar suara-suara.
Can you tell what they’re saying?
Tahu apa katanya?
There aren't any voices, Harry.
Tak dengar apa-apa, Harry.
Let’s get out of here.
Ayo keluar dari sini.
I hear them too.
Kudengar suara-suara juga.
Harry, it’s just an empty archway.
Harry, itu cuma lengkungan kosong.
Please, Harry.
Sudahlah, Harry.
Get behind me.
Semua di belakangku!
Did you actually believe...
Kau benar-benar percaya....
...or were you truly naive enough to think...
Maksudku, kau benar-benar naif berpikir...
...that children stood a chance against us?
...anak-anak berkemungkinan mengalahkan kami?
I'll make this simple for you, Potter.
Baiklah kuberi pilihan mudah bagimu, Potter.
Give me the prophecy now...
Serahkan bola ramalan itu padaku sekarang...
..-or watch your friends die.
...atau saksikan teman-temanmu mati.
Don't give it to him, Harry.
Jangan diserahkan, Harry!
Get away from my godson.
Menjauh dari anak-baptisku!
Now, listen to me. Take the others and get out of here.
Bawa teman-temanmu keluar dari sini.
What? No, I'm staying with you.
Tidak. Aku bersamamu.
You've done beautifully.
Tindakanmu tadi berani.
Now, let me take it from here.
Sekarang giliranku.
Black.
Black.
Expelliarmus!
Expelliarmus!
Nice one, James.
Mantera bagus, James!
Avada Kedavra.
Avada Kedavra.
No. No.
Tidak. Tidak.
I killed Sirius Black.
Kubunuh Sirius Black!
-You coming to get me? -Crucio.
-Mau melawanku? -Crucio.
You've got to mean it, Harry.
Kau harus benar-benar menginginkannya, Harry.
She killed him. She deserves it.
Dia bunuh Black. Pantas disiksa.
You know the spell, Harry.
Kau tahu manteranya, Harry.
Do it.
Kutuk dia!
So weak.
Lemah sekali.
It was foolish of you to come here tonight, Tom.
Bodoh kau kemari malam ini, Tom.
The Aurors are on their way.
Para Auror sedang menuju kemari.
By which time I shall be gone, and you...
Saat itu aku sudah pergi dan kau...
... shall be dead.
...Sudah mati!
You've lost, old man.
Kau sudah kalah, Pak Tua.
Harry.
Harry.
So weak.
Begitu lemah.
So vulnerable.
Begitu rapuh.
Look at me.
Pandang aku.
Harry, it isn’t how you are alike.
Harry, bukan soal kau dan dia ada persamaannya.
It's how you are not.
Melainkan betapa berbedanya kalian.
Harry?
Harry?
You're the weak one...
Kau yang lemah...
..-and you'll never know love or friendship.
...dan takkan pernah tahu kasih dan persahabatan.
And I feel sorry for you.
Aku merasa kasihan padamu.
You're a fool, Harry Potter.
Kau bodoh, Harry Potter.
And you will lose everything.
Kau akan kehilangan segalanya.
He’s back.
Dia kembali.
I know how you feel, Harry.
Aku tahu perasaanmu, Harry.
No, you don't.
Anda tidak tahu.
It's my fault.
Ini kesalahan saya.
No, the fault is mine.
Bukan, ini kesalahanku.
I knew it was only a matter of time...
Aku tahu Voldemort suatu saat...
...before Voldemort made the connection between you.
...akan bisa baca kenanganmu.
I thought by distancing myself from you, as I have done all year...
Kupikir dengan menjauhimu seperti yang kulakukan setahun ini...
...he’d be less tempted, and therefore you might be more protected.
...akan berkurang nafsu menyerangnya dan kau lebih terlindungi.
The prophecy said:
Menurut ramalan:
“Neither one can live while the other one survives.”
“Takkan ada yang bisa hidup selagi yang satunya masih hidup."
It means one of us is gonna have to kill the other, in the end.
Berarti satu dari kami harus membunuh yang lainnya.
Yes.
Ya.
Why didn't you tell me?
Mengapa tak beritahu saya?
For the same reason you tried to save Sirius.
Karena alasan yang sama kauselamatkan nyawa Sirius.
The same reason your friends saved you.
Alasan yang sama teman-temanmu menyelamatkanmu.
After all these years, after all you've suffered...
Setelah segala penderitaanmu bertahun-tahun ini...
...[ didn’t want to cause you . any more pain.
...aku tak mau membuatmu disakiti lagi.
l cared too much about you.
Aku terlalu sayang padamu.
How come you're not at the feast?
Mengapa tak ikut pesta?
Lost all my possessions. Apparently people have been hiding them.
Semua milikku hilang. Ada yang menyembunyikannya.
That's awful.
Kasihan kau.
Oh, it’s all good fun.
Ah, cuma canda.
But as it’s the last night, l really do need them back.
Tetapi ini malam terakhir, jadi kuingin semua dikembalikan.
Do you want any help finding them?
Mau kubantu menemukannya?
I'm sorry about your godfather, Harry.
Aku menyesal tentang ayah-baptismu, Harry.
Are you sure you don't want any help looking?
Sungguh tak mau kubantu?
That's all right.
Tak usahlah.
Anyway, my mum always said...
Kata ibuku...
...the things we lose have a way of coming back to us in the end.
...yang hilang akhirnya akan kembali lagi pada kita.
If not always in the way we expect.
Walau tak seperti yang kita harapkan.
Think I'll just go have some pudding.
Aku mau makan puding saja.
I've been thinking about something Dumbledore said to me.
Kupikirkan ucapan Dumbledore padaku.
What's that?
Apa katanya?
That even though we've got a fight ahead of us...
Walau kelak kita harus menghadapi pertarungan besar...
...we've got one thing that Voldemort doesn’t have.
...kita punya satu hal yang tak dimiliki Voldemort.
Yeah?
Ya?
Something worth fighting for.
Sesuatu yang layak kita perjuangkan.
[ENGLISH]
IINDONESIANJ